…大家注意，暴風仍在向西移動
... and I'll tell you what, the storm system's still moving west.
在看什麼呢，卡洛琳？
What are you looking at, Caroline?
看風，媽媽
The wind, Mom.
他們說颶風要來了
They say the hurricane is coming.
我感覺像在一艘船上
I'm on a boat.
漂浮著
I'm drifting.
我可以做什麼嗎，媽媽？
Can I do anything for you, Mom?
讓你舒服點？
Make anything easier?
哦，寶貝…
Oh, sugar...
沒什麼可做的
There's nothing left to do.
就這樣吧
Is what it is.
我越來越睜不開眼了
Finding it harder to keep my eyes open.
嘴裡像是塞滿了棉花
My mouth's full of cotton.
好了，好了，黛西女士
There, there, Miss Daisy.
你快把自己抓傷了
You gonna scratch yourself to ribbons.
藥還要嗎，媽媽？
Do you want any more medication, Mother?
醫生說用多點沒關係
Doctor said you could have as much as you want.
這樣大家都不會遭罪
No need for anybody to suffer.
有個朋友說過，她甚至都沒有機會
A friend told me that she never had the chance
跟她母親道別
to say goodbye to her mother.
- 我想… - 沒事
- I wanted to... - It's okay.
我想告訴你，我會非常想念你的…
I wanted to tell you how much I'm gonna miss you so...
媽媽
Mom.
哦，卡洛琳
Oh, Caroline.
你怕嗎？
Are you afraid?
我很好奇
I'm curious.
接下來會怎樣？
What comes next?
火車站建於1918年
They built the train station in 1918.
開站那天我父親也去了
My father was there the day it opened.
他說那天還請了
He said they had
銅管樂隊表演
a tuba band playing.
還請來了整個南方最好的鐘錶匠
They had the finest clockmaker in all of the South
建了那座雄偉的大鐘
to build that glorious clock.
那人叫…
His name was...
蓋圖先生
Mr. Gateau.
蛋糕先生 （蓋圖/Gateau在法語中是蛋糕之意）
Mr. Cake.
他娶了伊文格琳縣一個克裡奧爾人
He was married to a Creole of Evangeline Parish
後來他們生了個兒子
and they had a son.
蓋圖先生先天失明
Mr. Gateau was, from birth, absolutely blind.
他們的兒子長大後就參了軍
When their son was old enough, he joined the army.
他們向上帝祈禱，保佑他平安
And they prayed God would keep him out of harm's way.
好幾個月，他除了建那鐘，什麼都沒做
For months, he did nothing but work on that clock.
然後有一天
One day,
他們收到一封信
a letter came.
那天晚上工作完後
And Mr. Gateau, done for the night,
蓋圖先生就獨自去睡覺了
went up, alone, to bed.
然後他們的兒子回來了
And their son came home.
他們把他埋在家族墓地裡
They buried him in the family plot,
等他們死後，一家就能團聚了
where he would be with them when their time came.
蛋糕先生繼續建造那座鐘
Mr. Cake worked on his clock,
耗盡心血，終於完工
laboring to finish.
那是一個值得紀念的早上
It was a morning to remember.
爸爸說，那天人山人海
Papa said there were people everywhere.
連泰迪·羅斯福都來了
Even Teddy Roosevelt came.
鐘倒走了！
It's running backwards!
我故意這麼做的
I made it that way
這樣那些在戰爭中死去的孩子們
so that perhaps the boys that we lost in the war
也許就會死而復生，回家來
might stand and come home again.
回家耕種
Home to farm,
工作
work,
生兒育女
have children.
過完他們漫長而充實的一生
To live long, full lives.
也許我自己的兒子也能回家來
Perhaps my own son might come home again.
如有得罪，請各位原諒
I'm sorry if I've offended anybody.
希望你們喜歡我的鐘
I hope you enjoy my clock.
蛋糕先生自此再沒出現過
Mr. Cake was never seen again.
有人說他心碎而死
Some say he died of a broken heart.
有人說他出海了
Some say he went to sea.
對不起
Excuse me.
我可以打個電話嗎？我孩子請人照看著
Do you mind if I make a call? Somebody's watching my little boy.
當然
Sure.
希望我沒讓你失望
I hope I haven't disappointed you.
你不會讓我失望的
You couldn't disappoint me.
我知道自己沒什麼才能
Well, I know I don't have much to show for myself.
把我的黑色手提箱找出來
Find my dark suitcase.
裡面有本日記
There's a diary.
這個嗎？
This?
能念給我聽聽嗎？
Could you read it to me?
你就想這樣？
Is this what you want to do?
我讀過無數次了
I tried to read it a hundred different times.
媽媽，這並不是…
Mom, it's not exactly...
只是想聽聽你的聲音，親愛的
It's just the sound of your voice, darling.
好吧
Okay.
時間是1985年4月4日
It's dated April 4th, 1985.
上面寫著新奧爾良
And it says New Orleans.
“這是我最後的遺言，也是遺囑
"This is my last will and testament.
“我沒留下什麼，沒財產，沒錢，真的
"I don't have much to leave, few possessions, no money, really.
“我孤獨地來，孤獨地去 生不帶來，死不帶去
"I will go out of this world the same way I came in, alone and with nothing.
“我僅有的就是我的故事
"All I have is my story,
“我現在就寫著，趁我還記得的時候
"and I'm writing it now while I still remember it.
“我的名字叫本傑明，本傑明·巴頓”
"My name is Benjamin. Benjamin Button."
我的出生很不尋常
And I was born under unusual circumstances.
那時一戰剛結束
The First World War had ended,
後來我聽說，我出生的那個夜晚特別好
and I've been told it was an especially good night to be born.
謝天謝地終於結束了！
Thank God it's over!
我們贏了！
We won the war!
世界大戰結束了！
The Great War is over!
你來這幹嘛？
What are you doing here?
湯瑪斯
Thomas,
恐怕她快撐不住了
I'm afraid she's going to die.
什麼？
What?
夠了，你們都離她遠點
That's enough. All of you, get away from her.
我已經儘快趕回來了，街上盡是人
I came as quickly as I could. The streets are filled with people.
湯瑪斯
Thomas.
答應我，給他個容身之所
Promise me he has a place.
好的
Yeah.
她把生命給了我
She gave her life for me.
對此我畢生感激
And for that, I am forever grateful.
巴頓先生
Mr. Button.
湯瑪斯！
Thomas!
湯瑪斯
Thomas.
湯瑪斯？你去哪？
Thomas? Where are you going?
嘿！你在這幹嘛？
Hey! What are you doing there?
懷裡的是什麼？
What do you have there?
- 快點，奎尼 - 快，韋瑟斯先生！
- Come on, Queenie. - Now, Mr. Weathers!
得了，除了工作 我在這還有很多事要做
Come on, now, you know I ain't got nothing but work to do around here.
- 別，就一會 - 別犯傻了
- Come on. Just take some time. - Stop all this foolishness.
空氣真清新
The air is sweet.
你今晚真迷人，奎尼小姐
You look very handsome tonight, Miss Queenie.
一如既往的美
Handsome as I've ever seen.
棕色真配你的眼睛
The brown matches your eyes.
哦，討厭！
Oh, hush!
讓我瞧瞧，你也不賴啊
Let's see here. You ain't no slouch yourself.
漢伯特回鎮上了
Hambert's back in town.
他的兩條腿沒了，不過總算回來了
He came home legless, but he's home.
我知道你一度很迷戀他
I know you were sweet on him one time.
喜歡得都過頭了
Sweeter than I should've been.
西蒙妮小姐又尿褲子了
Miss Simone messed herself.
哦，我的小祖宗
Oh, sweet Jesus.
她可別這樣了，否則我要給她穿尿布了
She got to stop doing that or it's diapers for her.
- 我一會就去，詹姆森小姐！ - 快，奎尼，快來
- I'll be right there, Miss Jameson! - Now, Queenie, now come on.
好吧，奎尼馬上過來
Okay, Queenie'll be right there.
外面太舒服了
It's awful nice out here.
出來透透氣，別想那些事了
Come on out back for a moment. Take your mind off things.
你好壞
You're so bad.
- 上帝啊？ - 這是什麼？
- What in God's name? - What's this?
哦，上帝保佑
Oh, the Lord done something here.
希望我沒踩傷他
Hope I didn't hurt it none stepping on it like that.
我們最好交給員警處理
We best leave that for the police.
可憐的孩子
Poor baby.
我去找員警
I'll go.
肯定沒人願意收留他，來，寶貝
It's for sure nobody wanted to keep it. Come on, baby.
奎尼？你在哪，奎尼？
Queenie? Where are you, Queenie?
憋著！你去看下
Hold your water! You go deal with it.
好吧，不，你去，我馬上就來
Okay. No, go, I'll be back.
奎尼，蘋果她憋不住又尿了一身！
Queenie, Apple, she went and messed herself all over again!
簡·查爾裡斯，給她洗洗！
Jane Childress, start her a bath!
管好你自己的事，杜普雷太太
And mind your own business, Mrs. Duprey.
再沒多久你也一團糟了
You'll be messing yourself soon enough.
有人偷了我的項鍊
Somebody stole my necklace.
好的，知道了，霍利斯特太太 我一會就來，好嗎？
Okay. All right, Mrs. Hollister, I'll be right with you, okay?
回樓上去，聽見了嗎？
Go on back upstairs, hear?
你醜的像只舊罐子
You are as ugly as an old pot
可你仍是上帝的孩子
but you're still a child of God.
奎尼，你不在蘋果她不肯洗澡！
Queenie, Apple, she won't take a bath without you!
饒了我吧
Mercy.
我馬上就來！
I'll be right there!
好了，你就在這等我，好嗎？
Okay. You just wait right here for me now, okay?
我姐姐給了我那條珍珠項鍊 我怎麼也找不到
My sister gave me those pearls. I can't find them anywhere.
- 有人偷了我的珠寶 - 這這呢，霍利斯特夫人，看見了嗎？
- Somebody's been stealing my jewelry. - They're right here, Mrs. Hollister. See?
就掛在你那雪白漂亮的脖子上 好了，都別吵了
Right around your pretty white neck. Now, come on. Hush all that noise.
- 羅斯醫生還在這嗎？ - 不知道
- Is Dr. Rose still here? - I don't know.
你的心臟很健康
Your heart is strong.
只要避免過度刺激
You just want to avoid any undue stimulation.
我相信各位女士會照看好他的？
I trust you ladies will help me out with that?
我有事找您，您能下樓來一趟嗎？
I have something. Could you come downstairs?
從沒見過，白內障導致幾乎失明
Never seen anything like it. Nearly blind from cataracts.
我不確定他能不能聽見 從骨骼看他有嚴重的關節炎
I'm not sure if he can hear. His bones indicate severe arthritis.
他的皮膚完全沒有彈性，手腳都硬化了
His skin has lost all elasticity, and his hands and feet are ossified.
他的身體正在衰退，衰弱 一點都不像新生兒
He shows all the deterioration, the infirmities, not of a newborn,
更像是個80多歲行將踏進墳墓的老人
but of a man well in his 80s on his way to the grave.
他會死嗎？
He's dying?
生活還沒開始，他的身體就不行了
His body is failing him before his life's begun.
他從哪來？
Where'd he come from?
我姐姐的孩子，從拉斐特來（美國城市） 她遭遇了不幸
My sister's child. From Lafayette. She had an unfortunate adventure.
可憐的孩子，真是太不幸了，還是個白人
The poor child, he got the worst of it. Come out white.
有些地方專門收留這樣的棄兒，奎尼
There are places for unwanted babies like these, Queenie.
這兒沒地方再養一張嘴了
No room for another mouth to feed here.
儘管諾蘭基金會出於好意
The Nolan Foundation, despite their good intentions,
可他們還是覺得這地方是個大麻煩
thinks this place is a large nuisance as it is.
- 一個孩子… - 你剛說他活不長
- A baby... - You said he don't have long. - A baby... - You said he don't have long.
奎尼，有些生物註定無法存活
Queenie, some creatures aren't meant to survive.
不，這個孩子，他是個奇跡 這是肯定的
No, this baby, he is a miracle. That's for certain.
可惜不是那種大家期盼的奇跡
Just not the kind of miracle one hopes to see.
大家聽著，都聽好了
Y'all listen. Y'all listen up here.
我們有一位客人
We're gonna have us a visitor
要和我們住一段時間
that's gonna be staying with us for a little while.
我姐姐生了個孩子，她無法撫養，所以…
My sister had a child and she couldn't see right by it, so...
他的名字叫…
He's known as...
本傑明
Benjamin.
他的身體不好，我們得好好照顧他
He's not a well child, so we're gonna have to take good care of him.
我有過10個孩子
I had 10 children.
每個我都照顧得很好，讓我看看他
There's not a baby I can't care for. Let me see him.
天啊，他跟我前夫真像
God in Heaven. He looks just like my ex-husband.
看，他先天早衰
Look, he's prematurely old.
羅斯醫生說他活不久
Dr. Rose said he ain't got much more time on this earth.
歡迎加入俱樂部
Join the club.
他在笑！
He's smiling!
漢伯特讓我轉達他的問候
Hambert sends his remembrances to you.
你瘋了嗎？
Are you right out of your mind?
我知道你沒法有自己的孩子
I know you ain't got all the parts it takes to make one of your own,
可你也不能撫養這個
but this ain't yours to keep.
他一點都不像人
It may not even be humankind.
韋瑟斯先生，回來
Mr. Weathers, come back here.
求你了
Please.
你永遠也不清楚接下來會發生什麼
You never know what's coming for you.
看來我找到家了
It seemed I had found a home.
這都是真的嗎？
Is any of this true?
你的聲音真好聽
You have such a lovely voice.
媽媽，這有張舊電車票
Mom, it's an ancient streetcar token.
那座鐘一直走著
That clock just kept going,
年復一年
year after year after year.
可我不知道自己是個孩子
But I didn't know I was a child.
每天都是這些垃圾
Same old crap every day.
我以為自己和這裡的人一樣
I thought I was like everyone else there.
一個遲暮的老人
An old man in the twilight of his life.
你可以讓他停下嗎？
Could you make him stop that?
別敲叉子了，那是用來吃飯的 不是拿來玩的
Stop banging that fork. It's used for eating, not for playing with.
還有戴上餐巾，本傑明先生
And use your napkin, please, Mr. Benjamin.
奎尼！
Queenie!
嘿，小子
Hey, boy.
一直很好奇
Always had a healthy curiosity.
街上是什麼樣子的？下個街角又是怎樣的？
What was up the street? Or around the next corner?
去抓住他！
Go get him!
本傑明！那太危險了，快回來
Benjamin! That is dangerous. Come back over here.
別動，小子
Stay put, child.
我非常愛她
I loved her very much.
她是我的母親
She was my mother.
媽媽
Mama.
有時我覺得自己一天天地在改變
Some days I feel different than the day before.
每個人對於自己的感受都不一樣
Everybody feels different about themselves, one way or another.
但是我們的終點是一樣的
But we're all going the same way.
只是走的路不同罷了
Just taking different roads to get there, that's all.
你有你自己的道路，本傑明
You're on your own road, Benjamin.
媽媽？我還能活多久？
Mama? How much longer I got?
只要感謝上蒼賜予你的就行了，明白嗎？
Just be thankful for what you're given, hear?
你已經多活了
You're already here longer than you're supposed to.
有些晚上，我得一個人睡
Some nights, I'd have to sleep alone.
我並不介意
I didn't mind.
我在聆聽這個房子的呼吸
I would listen to the house breathing.
聽著大家沉睡的聲音
All those people sleeping.
我感到安心
I felt safe.
這裡的生活很有規律
It was a place of great routine.
每天早上5:30，不管天氣如何
Every morning at 5:30, no matter the weather,
美國退伍軍人溫斯洛將軍都會升旗
General Winslow, U.S. Army, Retired, would raise the flag.
曾經小有名氣的歌劇演員 西比爾·瓦格納夫人
Mrs. Sybil Wagner, once an opera singer of some note,
都會唱著瓦格納的歌劇
well, she sang Wagner.
好了，孩子，過來
All right, baby, come on.
我們來給你這雙老腿增加點活力
We got to put some life into these old sticks for you.
讓你能走路，這樣就可以幫我忙 來，明白嗎？
Get you walking so you can help me out around here. Come on now, hear?
一年四季，晚餐總是在5:30準時開始
No matter the season, supper was served promptly at 5:30.
（意思是糖漿，讀單詞中…）
Mo-lasses Molasses.
Molasses Molasses.
我五歲開始學著讀書
I learned to read when I was five.
我祖父曾是一個著名演員的化妝師
My grandfather was a dresser for a famous actor.
他會把每本劇本都帶回來給我看
He brung home every play for me to read.
“看守我這衰弱的老頭子的好人們
"Kind keepers of my weak decaying age,
“讓垂死的摩提默在這兒歇一歇吧
"Let dying Mortimer here rest himself.
“我由於長期監禁，肢體痛楚不堪
"Even like a man new haled from the rack,
“好像剛從刑架上拖下來的人一般
"So fare my limbs with long imprisonment.
“我這滿頭白髮 是在苦難的歲月中折磨出來的
"And these gray locks, the pursuivants of death,
“它預示著摩提默的死期不遠了”
"Argue the end of Edmund Mortimer."
你以為我不識字，對嗎？
You thought I was plain ignorant, didn't you?
我祖父侍奉的那個演員叫約翰·威爾克斯·布斯
The actor my grandfather worked for was John Wilkes Booth.
就是他殺了亞伯拉罕·林肯
He killed Abraham Lincoln.
世事難料
You never know what's coming for you.
週六晚上，媽媽會帶我去教堂
On Saturday nights, Mama would make me go to church.
本傑明！
Benjamin!
- 阿門！阿門！ - 阿門！阿門！
- Amen! Amen! - Amen! Amen!
有什麼需要幫忙的嗎，女士？
What can I do for you, sister?
她的內部器官有問題，無法生育
Her parts are all twisted up inside and she can't have little children.
主啊，如果您能寬恕這個女人的罪行
Lord, if you could see clear to forgive this woman her sins
就讓她孕育胎兒吧
so she can bear the fruit of the womb.
出來吧，該死的苦難！
Out, damnable affliction!
- 讚美主！ - 讚美主！
- Praise God! - Praise God!
哈利路亞！
Hallelujah!
- 哈利路亞！ - 哈利路亞！
- Hallelujah! - Hallelujah!
這位老人又有什麼苦？
And what's this old man's irrediction?
魔鬼纏上了他
He's got the Devil on his back,
想要提早把他趕進墳墓
trying to ride him into the grave before his time.
- 出來吧，魔鬼！ - 是的！
- Out, Zebuchar! - Yes!
- Out, Beelzebub! - Yes!
你多大了？
How old are you?
七歲，可我看起來要老得多
Seven. But I look a lot older.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
他只有七歲
He's seven.
這是一個樂觀向上的人
Now, this is a man with optimism in his heart.
- 是的 - 靈魂有所信仰！
- All right. - Belief in his soul!
- 是的！ - 是的！
- Yes! - Yes!
上帝的眼中我們都是孩子！
We are all children in the eyes of God!
- 是的！ - 哈利路亞！
- Yes! - Hallelujah!
我們得幫你擺脫那個輪椅
We are gonna get you out of that chair.
- 讓你能走路 - 阿門
- And we're gonna have you walk. - Amen.
沒事
It's all right.
以上帝的名義…
In the name of God's glory...
站起來！
Rise up!
加油
Come on.
加油，走起來
Come on. Walk.
加油，孩子，加油
Come on, son. Come on.
- 用力，孩子，加把勁 - 加油
- Come on with it, son. Come on. - Come on.
上帝會一路看著你的
Now God is gonna see you the rest of the way.
上帝會看著這個小老人 不靠拐杖輪椅，一路走下去
He's gonna see this little old man walk without the use of a crutch or a cane.
上帝會看著你…
He's gonna see that you walk from faith...
- 哈利路亞！ - 靠著信仰和保佑一個人走下去！
- Hallelujah! ...and divine inspiration alone!
- 是的 - 嗨，本！
- Yes. - Hey, Ben!
- 去吧，孩子！ - 走走看
- Go, son! - Now walk.
- 太好了 - 繼續
- Yes. - Come on.
別碰他
Don't touch him.
站起來，老傢伙
Rise up, old man.
像拉撒路那樣站起來
Rise up like Lazarus.
給我站起來！
I said, rise up!
哈利路亞！
Hallelujah!
是的
Yes.
加油
Come on.
說哈利路亞
Say hallelujah.
- 哈利路亞！ - 哈利路亞！
- Hallelujah! - Hallelujah!
走啊
Walk.
繼續走，對
Walk on. Yes.
就是這樣，本傑明
That's right, Benjamin.
每當我回想起這些，還是覺得是個奇跡
Now when I look back on it, it was miraculous.
有句話這麼說的，有得必有失
But you know the saying, the Lord giveth and the Lord taketh away.
讚美主啊！
Glory in the highest!
上帝啊！
Sweet Jesus!
- 不！ - 不！
- No! - No!
這有很多人過生日
There were so many birthdays.
他真是個快樂的好人 他真是個快樂的好人…
For he's a jolly good fellow For he's a jolly good fellow...
我們一般不出門，我們會省著用蠟燭
So we wouldn't run out, we would spare the candles.
奎尼，你知道我不喜歡生日 也不喜歡蛋糕
Queenie, you know I don't like birthdays and I don't like cake.
死亡也是這裡的常客 人們來到這裡，又安靜離去
And death was a common visitor. People came and went.
你可以感覺到有人離開了
You always knew when someone left us.
那時房子裡總是寂靜無聲
There was a silence in the house.
這是個值得成長的美好地方
It was a wonderful place to grow up.
在這個地方 人們拋開了過往生活中的矛盾
I was with people who had shed all the inconsequences of earlier life.
每天只關心天氣，洗澡水溫度
Left wondering about the weather, the temperature of a bath,
一天行將結束時的陽光
the light at the end of a day.
總會有人來重新填補死者的房間
For everyone that died, someone would come to take their place.
我結過5次婚
I've been married five times.
我和我的第五任妻子 被臨近的食人部落抓住了
My fifth wife and I are captured by a neighbor tribe of cannibals.
哦，天哪
Oh, goodness gracious.
我們從河裡逃跑
We escaped across the river.
我的妻子不會游泳，所以很不幸被吃了
My wife, she can't swim, so, sadly, she eaten.
哦，天啊
Oh, my God.
我的第二任妻子踩到了眼鏡蛇，就這麼死了
My second wife steps on cobra and dies.
嫁給我真是很不幸
It was very bad luck to be married to me.
那是歐緹先生，他是我一個熟人的熟人
That's Mr. Oti. He's an acquaintance of an acquaintance of mine.
- 第二年夏天我被… - 他是個矮人
- The next summer I'm captured... - He's a Pygmy.
…巴希勒部落的人抓了，還有其他三個人
...with three others by the Baschiele tribe.
他們用我們跟一個奇怪的美國人 換了豬，鞋子和啤酒
They trade us for pigs, shoes, and beer to a very strange American man.
聽說你並不像看起來那麼老
I hear you're not so old as you're looking.
大家都被你耍了
You just fooling everybody.
怎麼了？你有馬甲本嗎？
What's the matter? Did you get Madjembe?
什麼是馬甲本？
What's Madjembe?
蟲子
Worms.
我身上沒蟲子
I don't think I have worms.
我就是這樣的
This is just how I am.
- 今天吃藥了嗎？ - 沒有，夫人
- Did you take your pills today? - No, ma'am.
來，喝點冰汽水
Come. Let's get a cold root beer.
我在枕頭下找到了藥片
I found the medication under your pillow.
我不該去，太危險了
I'm not supposed to. It's dangerous.
誰說的？來，小傢伙
Who said that? Come on, little man.
孩子們好
Hello, children.
等等
Hold, please.
我和費城動物園的猴子關在一起
Then I'm in the monkey house at Philadelphia Zoological Park.
第一天就有3000人來
Three thousand people show up my first day.
看
Look.
住籠子裡是什麼感覺？
What's it like living in a cage?
臭死了
It stinks.
可是有猴子
But the monkeys.
他們會表演戲法
They do some tricks there.
我扔矛，和科瓦利打架
I throw a spear, wrestle with Kowali.
她是只母猩猩
She is orangutan.
不和猴子玩的時候，他們就把我趕回籠子
When I'm not playing with the monkeys, they want me to run to the bars
讓我咬來咬去
in my cage, with my teeth.
之後呢？
So then what'd you do?
後來我離開了動物園，這兒走走 那兒走走，四處遊蕩
Then I leave zoo, go here, go there. Wandered most of the time.
獨自一個人？
You were all alone?
大多數時候都是一個人的
Plenty of time you'll be alone.
像我們這樣的異類，就是這樣
When you're different like us, it's gonna be that way.
告訴你個小秘密
But I'll tell you a little secret.
無論什麼膚色，什麼體型
Fat people, skinny people, tall people,
人都是孤獨的
white people, they're just as alone as we are.
但可怕的不是孤獨，而是懼怕孤獨
But they're scared shitless.
我想起了伴我長大的那條河
I think about the river I grew up on.
再次坐在河邊感覺一定很妙
It would be nice to sit by my river again.
走吧，我約了人
Come, I have an appointment.
我的小傢伙來了，準備好了嗎，寶貝？
There's my little man. You ready, sugar?
時刻準備著，時刻準備著
Always ready. Always ready.
菲拉門娜，本傑明先生
Filamena, Mr. Benjamin.
- 很高興見到你，先生 - 我的榮幸，夫人
- It's a pleasure to meet you, sir. - My pleasure, ma'am.
你認得路回家，對嗎？
You can find your own way home, can't you?
乘聖查理斯線到拿破崙路
Take the St. Charles line to Napoleon.
嘿！嘿！
Hey! Hey!
你到底去哪了？進來
Where in God's name have you been? Get in here.
我急死了，知道嗎？
I mean, you take my breath away, you know that?
哦，天啊，我擔心死了
Oh, Lord, I was so worried about you.
這是我過得最開心的一天
It had been the best day of my life.
- 她的呼吸情況如何？ - 很微弱
- How's her breathing? - It's shallow.
他們幾小時後會到
They say it'll reach us in a few hours,
所以我得把我孩子帶到姐姐那去
so I gotta get my baby and take him to my sister's.
他們說醫院裡沒什麼好擔心的
They say there's nothing to worry about here in the hospital.
若需要，護士會馬上過來，你還好吧？
Nurses'll be right here if you need them. Are you okay?
- 沒事，我可以讀書 - 一小時內我就會回來
- Yeah, I'm okay reading. - I shouldn't be more than an hour.
有人來陪了嗎？
Was there just company?
是桃樂茜要走了
It was just Dorothy leaving.
繼續，卡洛琳
Go on, Caroline.
“星期天，所有的家人都會來”
"On Sundays, the families would come and visit."
那是1930年的感恩節
It was Thanksgiving, 1930.
我遇見了那個改變我一生的人
I met the person who changed my life forever.
本傑明
Well, Benjamin.
你看上去真是出奇地年輕啊
Might I say you are looking strikingly youthful.
你好，富勒太太
Good day, Mrs. Fuller.
一根拐杖，背也直了
A single cane, back straight as an arrow.
你吃了什麼靈丹妙藥？
What elixir have you been drinking?
- 謝謝，夫人 - 奶奶！看看我！
- Thank you, ma'am. - Grandma! Look at me!
真不錯
That was really something.
快過來
Come on over here, you.
這是我孫女，黛西
Now, this is my granddaughter, Daisy.
這位是…
This is Mr...
不好意思，本傑明，我還不知道你姓什麼
I'm afraid, Benjamin, I don't rightly know your last name.
叫我本傑明就行了
Benjamin's fine.
我永遠忘不了她那雙藍眼睛
I never forgot her blue eyes.
各位，晚餐準備好了
Good people, supper is served.
為了健康和食物，為了愛和友誼 為了上帝賜予的一切
Health and food, for love and friends. For everything thy goodness sends.
阿門
Amen.
- 阿門！ - 阿門！
- Amen! - Amen!
你們知道火雞並不是鳥嗎？
Did you know turkeys aren't really birds?
怎麼說？
Why do you say that?
他們屬於雉科，基本不會飛
They're in the pheasant family, can't hardly fly.
不覺得這很可憐嗎？不會飛的鳥？
It's sad, don't you think? Birds that can't fly?
我喜歡不會飛的鳥
I love birds that can't fly.
非常美味
They are so delicious.
- 你太壞了 - 在我們向主感謝恩賜之時
- That's terrible. - I have something to tell y'all
我有件事要宣佈
while we're giving thanks for God's blessings.
奇跡在我身上發生了
I had a miracle happen.
主回應了我的祈禱
The Lord saw fit to answer my prayers.
什麼叫回應了她的祈禱？
What does she mean, answered her prayers?
謝謝，謝謝
Thanks. Thank you.
她有孩子了，傻瓜
She's gonna have a baby, silly.
我媽媽懷上弟弟的時候也這麼說過
That's what my mama said when I was gonna have a baby brother,
可他沒活多久
but he didn't live long,
因為他的呼吸有問題
'cause he didn't breathe right.
“下午他長出了漂亮的後腿 （選自吉卜林創作的兒童作品故事集中的老袋鼠之歌）
"In the afternoon, when he had got his beautiful hind legs
“就如大神農答應過的
"just as Big God Nqong had promised.
“時間正好是5點
"You can see that it is 5:00,
“大神農的鐘上就是這樣”
"because Big God Nqong's clock says so."
很神奇吧？
Isn't that something?
再講一遍
Again, read it again.
哦，再講一遍吧
Oh, read it again, please.
好吧，不過講完之後，你們必須去睡覺
All right. But afterwards, you must go to bed.
我保證
I promise.
“老袋鼠”
"Old Man Kangaroo."
你睡著了嗎？
Are you sleeping?
誰？
Who's that?
是我，黛西
It's me, Daisy.
哦，嗨！
Oh, hi!
過來
'Kay, come on.
我們去哪？
Where are we going?
來，到這下麵
Come on. Under here.
給，把這點上
Here, you light it.
我不該玩火柴
I'm not supposed to play with matches.
別那麼膽小，快點
Don't be a chicken. Light it.
我跟你說個秘密，你也跟我說個
I'll tell you a secret if you'll tell me one.
好啊
Okay.
我看見我媽媽吻了一個男人
I saw my mama kissing another man.
她臉都紅了
Her face was red from it.
該你了
Your turn.
我並沒有看上去那麼老
I'm not as old as I look.
我也這麼覺得
I thought so.
你不像個老人
You don't seem like an old person.
- 比如我奶奶那樣 - 沒錯
- Like my grandma. - I'm not.
你病了？
Are you sick?
我聽見媽媽和蒂奇私下聊天
Well, I heard Mama and Tizzy whispering.
他們說我活不久了，但或許又不是
They said I was gonna die soon, but maybe not.
你真奇怪
You're odd.
你和我見過的人不一樣
You're different than anybody I've ever met.
- 可以嗎？ - 當然
- May I? - Okay.
你們在下面幹嘛？
What are you doing under there?
快回床上去！
You come right out here and get back up to bed!
都大半夜了！
It's after midnight!
不可以再一起玩了
You are not to be playing together.
是，夫人
Yes, ma'am.
快回床上去，小姑娘
Now you get back to bed, little lady.
你還太小，半夜不能一個人出來亂跑
You're too young to be wandering around in the night on your own.
還有你該為自己感到羞愧
And you ought to be ashamed of yourself.
你跟別的小孩不一樣
You are a different child.
有著大人外表，卻還是個孩子
A man-child.
孩子，別人是不會明白你的不一樣的
And, baby, people aren't gonna understand just how different you are.
我怎麼了，媽媽？
What's wrong with me, Mama?
過來
Come here.
上帝也沒說，孩子
God hasn't said yet, baby.
快回床上，好嗎？乖點
Now go on to bed, hear? And behave yourself.
去吧，別忘了祈禱，聽見了嗎？
Go on. Say your prayers, hear?
我跟你說過我曾被閃電擊過7次嗎？
Did I ever tell you I've been struck by lightning seven times?
一次是在修屋頂
Once when I was repairing a leak on the roof.
一次是在過馬路取信
Once I was just crossing the road to get the mail.
我永遠忘不了她那雙…
I never forgot her...
“…藍眼睛”
"...blue eyes."
媽媽？
Mom?
這個本傑明是不是對你一見鍾情啊？
Did you get that this Benjamin loved you from the first time that he saw you?
很少人會有這種經歷
Not many people experience that.
要我繼續嗎？
Want me to go on?
他劃掉了一些
He crosses something out.
那個孩子到來後，一切變得不同了
When that baby came, things were different.
你媽媽走了，你爸爸還在
Your mama gone away And your daddy gonna stay
孩子也在
Didn't leave nobody but the baby
有人出生，有人死亡
Babies were born, people died.
許多人進出過那所老房子
A lot of folks been through that old house.
我是來道別的，我要走了
I've come to say goodbye. I'm going away.
走？
Going?
去哪？
Where?
還沒想好
I haven't figured that out yet,
不過我會給你寄明信片
but I'll send you a postcard when I get there.
你的朋友怎麼辦，那個高個子的女人？
What about your friend, the tall lady?
我們已經不是朋友了
We are not friends anymore.
高個子的人有時就這樣
That's what happens with tall people sometimes.
好吧，再見
Well, goodbye.
那年我就是一個人這麼過來的
Spent a lot of time by myself that year.
有人嗎？
Hello?
- 你好 - 我今天剛搬來
- Hi. - I'm moving in today.
歡迎，我們等你很久了
Welcome. We've been expecting you.
你能帶她去盧梭太太住過的那間嗎？
Can you please show her up to Mrs. Rousseau's old room?
抱歉，我們這裡是不許養狗的
I'm sorry, but we usually don't allow dogs in the house.
她已經很老了，都快瞎了
Well, she's old as the hills. She's almost blind.
不會麻煩你們很久
She won't be a bother much longer.
好吧，只要不礙事待多久都行
Well, all right, long as she stays from up underfoot.
這邊，夫人
Right this way, ma'am.
我想了很久也沒想起她叫什麼
As hard as I try, I can't remember her name.
勞森太太還是哈特福德太太
Mrs. Lawson, or Mrs. Hartford.
也許是梅普爾太太
Maybe it was Maple.
很有意思，有時候我們最記不得的人
It's funny how sometimes the people we remember the least
卻印象最深
make the greatest impression on us.
我清楚記得她戴著鑽戒
I do remember she wore diamonds.
總是穿得很漂亮，像要出門一樣
And she always dressed in fine clothing, as if she was going out.
但她從沒出過門，也沒人來看她
Although she never did and nobody ever came to visit her.
她教我彈鋼琴
She taught me to play the piano.
無所謂你彈奏得怎樣
It's not about how well you play.
重要的是你彈琴時的感受
It's how you feel about what you're playing.
試試看
Try this.
情不自禁沉浸於音樂中
You can't help putting yourself in the music.
變化是無窮的
There were many changes.
有些看得到，有些看不到
Some you could see, some you couldn't.
比如頭髮會四處生長
Hair had started growing in all sorts of places,
還有很多其他的事物
along with other things.
我感覺很棒
I felt pretty good, considering.
親愛的，痛
Darling, the pain.
好的，媽媽，我去叫護士
All right, Mom, I'll get the nurse.
看看風眼，這是強烈颶風
Look at this eye. This is a major hurricane,
颶風移動不快，伴隨最大持續風…
a slow hurricane, with maximum sustained winds of...
感覺不好？
Not doing too good?
似乎沒人知道該走還是該留
Nobody seems to know whether to stay or leave.
都會過去的
I'm gonna ride it out.
好了，讓她舒服點
There. That should make things much easier.
道過別了嗎？
Have you had a chance to say your goodbyes?
我父親等我弟弟從柏格市回來 等了四個小時 （位於美國北卡羅來納州林肯郡）
My father waited four hours for my brother to get here from Boger City.
想見他最後一面
Couldn't go without him.
- 她看上去很安詳 - 是啊
- She seems like a sweet woman. - Yeah.
我應該多陪陪她的…
I haven't had as much time with her as I would've...
- 忙嗎？過來幫我下 - 失陪
- You busy? I could use your help. - Excuse me.
沒關係
Sure.
奎尼會同意我跟道斯先生…
"Queenie would let me go with Mr. Daws..."
去波弗蒂角看船 （路易斯安那州內印地安人遺址）
... to Poverty Point to watch the boats go up and down the river.
這些日子不好過
These were hard times.
我跟你說過我曾被閃電擊了7次嗎？
Did I ever tell you I was struck by lightning seven times?
一次是在田裡放牛
Once when I was in the field, just tending to my cows.
我的夥計沒來
My fourth hand didn't show up.
有人想在這打工賺個2塊錢嗎？
Anybody want to make $2 for a day's work 'round here?
怎麼了？
What's the matter?
沒人想勤懇工作賺這一天的工錢？
Nobody wants to do an honest day's work for an honest day's pay?
他從不給錢
He never pays.
- 沒人要做？ - 我做
- Nobody wants a job? - I do.
你不暈船吧，老頭？
You got your sea legs about you, old man?
我想是的
I think.
很好，這就夠了
Well, that's good enough for me.
快上船，上來就知道了
Get your ass on board. We'll sure as hell find out.
我從沒這麼開心過
I was as happy as I could be.
誰來幫忙！
I need a volunteer!
我什麼都做
I would do anything.
是，船長！
Yes, Captain!
把鳥屎都刮了！
Scrape off all this bird shit!
馬上，先生
Right away, sir.
事實上，本沒報酬的我卻拿到了
And I was actually gonna be paid for something I would've done for free.
他是邁克·克拉克船長
His name was Captain Mike Clark.
7歲起就在拖船上了
He'd been on a tugboat since he was seven.
上來
Get moving, then.
過來
Come here.
你還能勃起嗎？
Can you still get it up?
每天早上都行
I do every morning.
就憑這根，哈？能豎得老高老硬的？
The old pole, huh? The high, hard one?
我想是的
I guess.
你上一次碰女人是什麼時候？
When was the last time you had a woman?
- 從沒碰過 - 從沒碰過？
- Never. - Never?
我記得沒有，先生
Not that I know of, sir.
等等
Wait a minute, now.
你是說你活了這麼多年
You mean to say you've been on this earth however many years
還沒上過女人？
and you've never had a woman?
見鬼，這是我聽過最慘的事了
Damn, that's the saddest thing I've ever heard in my life.
從沒碰過？
Never?
沒有
No.
好吧，你得感謝老天爺讓你遇上我
Well, then, by Jesus, you are coming with me.
你父親做什麼的？
What did your father do?
我從沒見過我父親
I never met my father.
你這走運的雜種
You lucky bastard.
做父親的都想壓制兒子
All fathers want to do is hold you down.
我在我父親的船上日夜做工
Out on my father's boat, workin' the two-a-day,
這個混蛋胖子
this little, fat bastard.
別人都叫他“愛爾蘭苦力”
"Tug Irish," they called him.
不過最後我終於鼓足勇氣跟他說
Anyway, I finally work up the nerve and tell him,
“我不想把我的一輩子都浪費在這破船上”
"I don't want to spend the rest of my life on a goddamn tugboat."
知道我的意思嗎？
You know what I'm saying?
你不想把一輩子浪費在破船上
You don't want to spend the rest of your life on a tugboat.
對！就是這樣！
Absolutely! Damn right!
那你知道我爸怎麼回答嗎？
So you know what my father says to me?
他說，“你他媽以為自己是誰？
He says, "Who the hell do you think you are?
“你他媽以為自己能做什麼？”
"What the hell do you think you can do?"
然後我告訴他
So I tell him.
“既然你問了
"Well, if you're asking,
“我想當藝術家”
"I want to be an artist."
他笑了
He laughs.
“藝術家？你就是幹拖船的命 就和我一樣"
"An artist? God meant for you to work a tugboat, just like me.
“老老實實地給我幹活”
"And that's exactly what you're gonna do."
後來我真成了藝術家
Well, I turned myself into an artist.
一個紋身藝術家！
A tattoo artist!
這都是我自己紋的
I put on every one of these myself.
要拿走我的藝術，你得先活剝了我
You have to skin me alive to take my art away from me now.
我死後，要把自己的手臂給他
When I'm dead, I'm gonna send him my arm.
那條
That one.
讓別人去說吧
Don't let anyone tell you different.
想做什麼就去做
You gotta do what you're meant to do.
我碰巧就成了他媽的藝術家
And I happen to be a goddamned artist.
可你還是個拖船船長
But you're a tugboat captain.
邁克船長？
Captain Mike?
我們已經為你和你的朋友準備好了
We're ready for you and your friend.
走吧，老傢伙，去破你的身吧
Let's go, old timer, eh? Break your cherry.
- 好啊，甜心們！ - 嗨，船長
- Hello, my lovelies! - Hey, Captain.
- 嗨，船長 - 嗨
- Hi, Captain. - Hi.
- 嗨 - 嗨
- Hi. - Hi.
好噁心，我才不要
He gives me the willies. That is not for me.
今晚過得如何，老爺爺？
How are you tonight, grandpa?
那是一個難忘的夜晚
It was a night to remember.
你是什麼，狄克·崔西還是什麼？ 我得休息休息
What are you, Dick Tracy or something? I've got to rest.
再來
Again.
- 謝謝 - 不，該謝謝你，你今晚過得不錯
- Thank you. - No, thank you. You have a nice night.
- 明天你還在嗎？ - 除了星期天每天都在
- Will you be here tomorrow? - Every night but Sunday.
我想我明白了掙錢的重要
It sure made me understand the value of earning a living.
晚安，寶貝，再來哦
Good night, sweetie. Come back now.
錢能買到一切
Things money can buy you.
外面髒
It's nasty out.
要搭車嗎？
Can I offer you a ride somewhere?
您真是太好了，先生
Well, that's awfully kind of you, sir.
我叫湯瑪斯，湯瑪斯·巴頓
My name is Thomas, Thomas Button.
- 我叫本傑明 - 本傑明
- I'm Benjamin. - Benjamin.
很高興認識你
It's a pleasure to know you.
願意停下去喝杯嗎？
Would you like to stop somewhere and have a drink?
好啊
All right.
晚上好，巴頓先生
Evening, Mr. Button.
要點什麼，先生？
What'll it be, sir?
- 跟他一樣 - 給我們都來薩澤拉克雞尾酒
- I'll have whatever he's having. - Sazerac for the both of us.
加威士卡，不要白蘭地
With whiskey, not brandy.
你不喝酒？
You don't drink, do you?
- 今晚什麼都是第一次啊 - 怎麼說？
- It's a night for firsts. - How's that?
以前從沒找過妓女
I've never been to a brothel, either.
這是種經歷
Well, it's an experience.
當然，凡事總有第一次
It certainly is. There's a time for everything.
- 沒錯 - 你們的酒
- True enough. - Your drinks.
恕我冒昧，你的手，痛嗎？
I don't mean to be rude, but your hands. Is that painful?
我生來就有些病
Well, I was born with some form of disease.
什麼病？
What kind of disease?
我天生就是老頭
I was born old.
- 抱歉 - 沒關係
- I'm sorry. - No need to be.
年老沒什麼錯
There's nothing wrong with old age.
我妻子多年前去世了
My wife passed away many years ago.
非常抱歉
I'm so, so sorry.
難產死的
She died in childbirth.
- 敬孩子 - 敬母親
- To children. - To mothers.
你幹哪行的，巴頓先生？
What line of work you in, Mr. Button?
紐扣，巴頓紐扣公司，我們生產各類紐扣
Buttons. Button's Buttons. There isn't a button that we don't make.
我們最大的競爭對手是B.F.富善公司
Our biggest competition is B.F. Goodrich
還有他們該死的拉鍊
and his infernal zippers.
先生們還要來點什麼嗎？
Would you gentlemen like anything else?
再來杯上路，本傑明？
One for the road, Benjamin?
這次算我的，巴頓先生
Only if you let me pay for it, Mr. Button.
那你是幹哪行的？
So, what line of work do you do?
我是個拖船工人
I'm a tugboat man.
跟你聊天很開心
I enjoyed talking to you.
跟你喝酒也很開心
I enjoyed drinking with you.
本傑明？
Benjamin?
我可以不時過來看看你嗎？
Would you mind if, time to time, I stopped by and said hello?
隨時歡迎，晚安，巴頓先生
Anytime. Good night, Mr. Button.
晚安，本傑明
Good night, Benjamin.
開車
Drive on.
你去哪了？
Where have you been?
沒什麼，遇到了個人，聽了會音樂
Nothing. I met some people and listened to some music.
哦，天啊，孩子！
Oh, sweet Jesus, boy!
長大是件很有意思的事 不經意間就發生了
Growing up's a funny thing. Sneaks up on you.
本來是這樣一個人 然後突然間變成了另一個人
One person is there, then suddenly somebody else has taken her place.
不再是原來那樣子
She wasn't all elbows and knees anymore.
本傑明！過來！
Benjamin! Come on!
來了
Okay.
我喜歡那些週末，她會來這裡
I loved those weekends when she'd come
和她的奶奶共度晚上
and spend the night with her grandmother.
黛西，黛西
Daisy. Daisy.
給你看些東西？
You want to see something?
不過你得保密 快穿好衣服，我在外面等你
You gotta keep it a secret, so get dressed. I'll meet you out back.
快點
Come on.
- 你會游泳嗎？ - 你會的我也會
- Can you swim? - I can do anything you can do.
給，穿上，我們得動作快點
Here, put this on. We gotta hurry.
他還好嗎？
Is he okay?
船長？
Captain?
邁克船長？
Captain Mike?
早上好，船長，能帶我們出海嗎？
Morning, Captain. Can you take us out?
知道今天星期幾嗎？
Do you know what day it is?
星期天？
Sunday?
知道那表示什麼嗎？
Do you know what that means?
意味著我昨晚喝醉了
Means I was very drunk last night.
你哪天不喝醉
Well, you're drunk every night.
- 是個女孩？ - 好朋友
- Is that a girl? - Close friend.
我想帶她看河
I want to show her the river.
你別偷偷帶外人出海
You're not supposed to go joyriding with civilians.
我會丟掉執照的
I could lose my license.
你還等什麼？
What are you waiting for?
要進站維修了
Pulled in for repair a wounded duck.
她在飛了，哈？
She's flying now, huh?
喂，水手！
Ahoy, sailor!
真希望能和他們一起去
I wish we could go with them.
你在說什麼，媽媽？
Did you say something, Mom?
天氣越來越糟
It's getting really bad.
能聽見嗎，媽媽？
Can you hear me, Mom?
我沒多少時間了
Time just seeped out of me.
“變化太快”
"Things were changing quickly."
不知怎麼回事，可你的頭髮多了
I don't know how it's possible, but you seem to have more hair.
要是我告訴你我沒有變老
What if I told you that I wasn't getting older,
而是變得更年輕了呢？
but I was getting younger than everybody else?
那真不幸
Well, I'd feel sorry for you,
你必須看著你愛的人先你而去
to have to see everybody you love die before you do.
真是可怕的責任
It's an awful responsibility.
我以前從沒想過生死
I'd never thought about life or death that way before.
本傑明，我們命中註定要失去所愛之人
Benjamin, we're meant to lose the people we love.
不然我們怎麼知道 他們在我們生命中有多重要？
How else would we know how important they are to us?
秋天的一天，死神不期而至
And one fall day, a familiar visitor came knocking on our door.
跟我一起去雜貨店嗎？
You want to go with me to the drugstore?
她教我彈鋼琴
She taught me how to play the piano.
- 阿門 - 阿門
- Amen. - Amen.
她讓我明白了失去一個人的感覺
And she taught me what it meant to miss somebody.
走吧
Let's go.
我去過妓院
I had gone to a brothel.
我喝過酒
I'd had my first drink.
跟一個朋友道別，跟另一個朋友永別
Said goodbye to one friend and buried another.
1936年我人生的第17個年末
In 1936, when I was coming to the end of the 17th year of my life,
我收拾了行裝跟大家告別
I packed my bag, said goodbye.
- 再見，本傑明 - 再見
- Bye, Benjamin. - Goodbye.
我知道，生活仍將繼續 也許我再也見不到他們了
I knew, life being what it was, I'd probably never see them again.
再見，本傑明先生
Bye, Mr. Benjamin.
- 祝你好運，兒子 - 謝謝
- Good luck to you, son. - Thank you.
- 我愛你，媽媽 - 我也愛你，寶貝
- I love you, Mama. - I love you, too, baby.
別忘了每晚做祈禱，好嗎？
I want you to say your prayers every night, hear?
平平安安的，聽見了嗎？
Be safe, hear?
本傑明！
Benjamin!
- 你去哪？ - 出海
- Where you going? - To sea.
我會給你寄明信片的
I'll send you a postcard.
無論在哪
From everywhere.
無論在哪都要給我寄明信片
Write me a postcard from everywhere.
你能想像嗎？
Can you imagine?
無論他去哪，在什麼地方工作
He sent me a postcard from everywhere he went.
都會給我寄明信片
Every place he worked.
紐芬蘭，巴芬灣
Newfoundland. Baffin Bay.
格拉斯哥，利物浦，納爾維克
Glasgow. Liverpool. Narvik.
他和邁克船長一起去的
He had gone with that Captain Mike.
邁克船長和莫蘭兄弟拖船打撈公司
Captain Mike had contracted for three years
簽了3年的合約
with Moran Brothers Tug and Salvage.
舊船裝上了柴油機和新的絞車
The old ship had been refitted with a diesel engine and a new sea winch.
我們繞過了佛羅里達 沿著大西洋海岸北上
We went around Florida and up the Atlantic seaboard.
船上現在有7名船員了，邁爾船長和我
We were a crew of seven now. Captain Mike and me.
廚師，來自德拉瓦州威靈頓的普蘭提斯·梅斯
Cookie, Prentiss Mayes from Wilmington, Delaware.
布羅迪雙胞胎，裡克和維克
The Brody twins, Rick and Vic,
在海上這兄弟倆相處很好 但不知什麼原因
who got along fine at sea but, for some reason,
一旦回到陸地，他們就不對盤
once they were on dry land couldn't stand the sight of each other.
你知道的，每八艘船就有一艘永遠回不來
You know, one in every eight boats never returns.
一個叫約翰·格林的，人如其名
There was John Grimm, who sure fit his name.
全體船員在海上失蹤了
All hands lost at sea.
來自南達科他州的貝爾維迪市
From Belvedere, South Dakota.
還有來自北卡羅來納州阿什維爾的 普萊森特·柯帝士
And Pleasant Curtis from Asheville, Notch.
從不跟人說話，除了他自己
Never said a word to anyone, except himself.
我經常給他寫信
I wrote him constantly. I wrote him constantly.
我告訴他我受邀參加紐約市
I told him I had been invited to audition in New York City
一所美國芭蕾學校的面試
for the School of American Ballet.
請留下
Please stay.
謝謝，謝謝
Thank you. Thank you.
你可以留下來
You can stay.
可我在團裡並不出名
But I was relegated to the corps.
只不過是個跳舞的流浪者
Another dancing gypsy.
本傑明！
Benjamin!
第一次見你時
How is it when you showed up
你比那個系船柱大不了多少 還一隻腳踩進了棺材
you were no bigger than a bollard with one foot in the grave,
而現在，是我喝多了
but now, either I drink a hell of a lot more than I think I do,
還是你長個了？
or you sprouted?
你有什麼秘密？
What's your secret?
船長
Well, Captain,
你確實喝多了
you do drink a lot.
我們住在一個小旅館裡 名字不錯，叫冬宮
We stayed in a small hotel with a grand name, The Winter Palace.
你根本不知道自己在說什麼
You have no idea what you're talking about.
蜂鳥不是一般的鳥類
The hummingbird is not just another bird.
它的心率達到每分鐘1200下
Its heart rate's 1,200 beats per minute.
它的翅膀每秒扇動80次
Its wings beat 80 times a second.
要是讓它無法扇動翅膀
If you was to stop their wings from beating,
不到10秒就會死掉
it would be dead in less than 10 seconds.
這不是一般的鳥
This is no ordinary bird.
簡直就是奇跡
This is a frickin' miracle.
人們用影像慢放扇翅膀的動作
They slowed down their wings with moving pictures,
知道他們看到了什麼？
and you know what they saw?
它們的翼尖像這樣運動
Their wingtips are doing that.
知道數字8有什麼數學含義嗎？
You know what the figure eight is the mathematical symbol for?
無窮
Infinity.
無窮！
Infinity!
每個人，不論語言和膚色有何差異
Everybody, no matter what differences they had,
卻都有一個共同點
the languages, the color of their skin, had one thing in common.
每晚都會喝醉
They were drunk every single night.
三樓，謝謝
Three, please.
能等一下嗎，親愛的？
Could you hold, dear, for us, please?
非常感謝，晚上好
Thank you very much. Good evening.
她叫伊莉莎白·亞伯特
Her name was Elizabeth Abbott.
她並不漂亮，很平凡
She was not beautiful. She was plain as paper.
但在我看來她很美
But she was pretty as any picture to me.
你在看什麼？
What are you looking at?
你該知道，我們有個長期協議
If you must know, we have a longstanding agreement
不醉不歸
never to go to bed sober.
- 對嗎，親愛的？ - 隨你怎麼說，親愛的
- Isn't that right, darling? - Whatever you say, darling.
她丈夫是沃爾特·亞伯特
Her husband was Walter Abbott.
他是英國貿易代表團在摩爾曼斯克的首席部長
He was Chief Minister of the British Trade Mission in Murmansk,
而且他還是個間諜
and he was a spy.
- 親愛的 - 哦，謝謝，親愛的
- Darling. - Oh, thank you, my darling.
- 鑰匙，親愛的 - 噢，對
- Key, darling. - Oh, yes.
我的一隻鞋跟斷了
I broke my heel off one of my shoes.
我不習慣只穿襪子走路
I'm not in the habit of walking about in my stocking feet.
那裡白天很長
They were long days there.
夜晚更加漫長
And even longer nights.
有一個晚上，我輾轉難眠
One particular night, I was having trouble sleeping.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我睡不著
I couldn't sleep.
我要去泡些茶，你要嗎？
I was gonna make some tea. Would you like some?
哦，不用了，謝謝
Oh, no. Thank you.
牛奶？還是蜂蜜？
Milk? Honey?
一點蜂蜜，謝謝
A bit of honey, please.
我希望你不介意蜂蜜裡有蒼蠅
I hope you like flies in your honey.
哦，還是算了
Oh, perhaps not.
哦，也許多浸一會會更好
Oh, maybe better to let it steep a little.
浸？
Steep?
浸泡
Soak.
我不知道，我的意思是，泡茶就該這樣
I don't know, I mean, there's a proper way of making tea.
我家鄉那都喜歡喝熱茶
Well, where I'm from, people just want it to be hot.
這樣啊
Well, quite right.
- 現在你是海員 - 水手
- Now, you're a seaman. - A sailor.
希望你不要介意，我忍不住想問
I hope you won't think me impolite, but I have to ask,
作為一個水手你是不是有點老？
aren't you a little old to be working on a boat?
沒有年齡限制，只要你能做
There's no age limit, as long as you can do the work.
你睡不好是嗎？謝謝
And you have trouble sleeping? Thank you.
以前不這樣，通常我睡得像嬰兒一樣沉
I didn't think I did. I usually sleep like a baby.
有些事讓我睡不著
Something's been keeping me up.
我父親80歲的時候
My father, in his 80s,
深信自己會在睡眠中死去
he was so convinced he was gonna die in his sleep,
他約束自己只睡午覺
he limited himself to having afternoon naps.
他堅信自己可以逃脫死亡
He was so determined he was gonna cheat death.
- 他做到了嗎？ - 做到什麼？
- Did he? - Did he what?
睡覺時死了？
Die in his sleep?
他死在自己最喜歡的椅子上
He died sitting in his favorite chair
聽著自己最喜歡的廣播節目
listening to his favorite program on the wireless.
他一定已經知道了
He must have known something.
我的丈夫是英國貿易部長 我們已經在這呆了14個月了
My husband's the British Trade Minister, and we've been here for 14 months.
- 天哪 - 本來我們要去北京的
- Good God. - We were supposed to go to Peking
可是看來永遠都無法成行了
but it never seemed to work out.
你去過遠東嗎？
Have you been in the Far East?
沒有，事實上我哪也沒去過
No. I've never been anywhere, really.
我是說，港口以外的地方
I mean, outside of harbors.
你從哪來？
And where is it that you're from?
路易斯安那州新奧爾良
New Orleans. Louisiana.
我知道那個地方
I didn't know there was another.
她跟我講了她去過的地方 還有她的所見所聞
And she told me about all the places she had been, and what she had seen.
我們一直聊到天亮
And we talked till just before the dawn.
我只是一個酒鬼
I'm just a lush, myself.
我們回到各自的房間，過各自的生活
And we went back to our rooms, to our separate lives.
可每晚我們都會在大廳見面
But every night, we'd meet again in that lobby.
午夜的旅館是一個神奇的地方
A hotel in the middle of the night can be a magical place.
老鼠在遠處跑跑停停
A mouse running, and stopping.
暖氣爐發出嘶嘶的響聲
A radiator hissing.
窗簾在沙沙作響
A curtain blowing.
這樣的場景讓你感到安靜，甚至是溫暖
There's something peaceful, even comforting
你知道你所愛的人此刻正在熟睡之中
knowing that the people you love are asleep in their beds
而沒有什麼可以傷害到他們
where nothing can harm them.
伊莉莎白和我都忘記了時間
Elizabeth and I would lose track of the night
直到黎明的到來
until just before daybreak.
我想我可能讓你誤解了
I think I may have given you the wrong impression.
什麼？
Beg pardon?
已婚女人通常不會在半夜
Well, married women don't customarily sit around
和陌生男人呆在旅館裡
in the middle of the night with strange men in hotels.
我不知道已婚女人什麼該做 什麼不該做
I wouldn't know what a married woman does or doesn't do.
晚安
Good night.
摩爾曼斯克
Murmansk.
“我遇見了一個人，我墜入了愛河”
"I've met somebody, and I've fallen in love."
媽媽？
Mom?
那是60多年前的事了
That was over 60 years ago.
你愛他嗎，媽媽？
Did you love him, Mother?
小女孩哪懂什麼愛情？
What does a girl know about love?
呃…
Well...
- 我穿得不好 - 哦，看起來蠻好，這才像你
- I'm not dressed. - Oh, you look splendid, just as you are.
在摩爾曼斯克，別浪費時間在酒和乳酪上
Don't waste any time bothering about the wine or the cheese in Murmansk,
因為這些實在很平常
'cause they're really completely ordinary,
但是魚子醬和伏特加
but the caviar and the vodka
更顯高貴奢華
are sublime and plentiful.
那麼
So.
好好嘗嘗
Savor it.
別一下子全吃了
And don't eat it all at once,
因為那樣是享受不到什麼的
because that way, there's nothing left to enjoy.
現在，口含伏特加，咽下一點點
And now, take a little swallow of vodka while it's still in your mouth.
你相處過的女人不多吧？
You haven't been with many women, have you?
星期天不多
Not on Sundays.
你以前從沒吃過魚子醬，對吧？
And you've never had caviar before, have you?
是的，夫人
No, ma'am.
我19歲時
When I was 19,
試圖成為第一個遊過英吉利海峽的女人
I attempted to become the first woman ever to swim the English Channel.
真的？
Really?
但那天的水流很急
But the current that day was so strong that,
向前遊一下，被水流推後兩下
for every stroke I took, I was pushed back two.
我在水裡待了32小時
I was in the water for 32 hours.
距離加來兩英里時
And when I was two miles from Calais,
天開始下雨了
it started to rain.
就是這樣！保持平穩！
That's it! Steady on!
我實在游不動時
When I couldn't go any further,
我停下了
I stopped.
我只好停下
I just stopped.
別人都問我，要不要再來一次？
And everybody asked me, would I try again?
為什麼不呢？
For why wouldn't I?
可我再沒有試過
But I never did.
事實上，自那以後我沒做過什麼
As a matter of fact, I've never done anything with my life after that.
你的手好粗糙
Your hands are so coarse.
我能感覺到吹向你臉頰的海風
I can feel the wind in your cheek.
恐怕已經到午夜了
I'm afraid it's the witching hour.
那是第一次有女人吻我
It was the first time a woman had ever kissed me.
難以忘懷
It's something you never forget.
是你讓我感覺年輕了
I think you make me feel younger.
你也讓我覺得年輕了好幾歲
You make me feel years younger, too.
希望如此
I wish I was.
我會改變很多事
So many things I'd change.
我會彌補所有的過錯
I'd undo all my mistakes.
什麼過錯？
What mistakes?
我一直等著，知道嗎？
I kept waiting, you know?
想著做些什麼改變自己的狀況
Thinking that I'd do something to change my circumstances.
做些什麼
Do something.
那些浪費掉的，一去不復返
Such an awful waste. You never get it back.
人生就這麼平白無辜地浪費了
Wasted time.
如果我們在一起
If we're going to have an affair,
白天千萬不要見面
you're never to look at me during the day.
日出之前我們一定要分開
And we're always to part before sunrise.
永遠不要說“我愛你”
And we will never say "I love you."
這些是規則
Those are the rules.
- 你冷嗎？ - 快凍僵了
- Are you cold? - I'm freezing.
哦，你！你快凍僵了
Oh, you! You're frozen.
真傻，我還穿著皮衣呢 我怎麼這麼粗心
What an idiot, I'm standing here in this fur. How thoughtless of me.
她是第一個愛過我的女人
She was the first woman that ever loved me.
要我跳過一些內容嗎？
You want me to skip some?
不用，我很高興有人能溫暖他
No, I'm glad he had somebody to keep him warm.
“我等不及要再見到她”
"I couldn't wait to see her again."
我們每晚見面
We saw each other every night.
總是在同一間屋子
We always used the same room.
可每次都有不同的體驗
But each time seemed new and different.
過來
Come here.
伊莉莎白
Elizabeth.
晚安
Good night.
直到有一個晚上
Until one night.
昨天，1941年12月7日
Yesterday, December 7th, 1941,
恥辱的一天…
a date which will live in infamy...
這是一場會議 一場事關未來的政治性會議
It's a meeting, a policy meeting regarding your future,
可能不止如此
possibly beyond.
夥計們，計畫有變
There's been a change of plan, lads.
你們或許知道，或許不知道
As you may or may not know,
日本人昨天轟炸了珍珠港
the Japs bombed Pearl Harbor yesterday.
佛蘭克林·德拉諾·羅斯福 要求我們每個人盡到自己的職責
Frank D. Roosevelt's asked each of us to do our part.
切爾西號被美國海軍徵用
The Chelsea's been commissioned to serve in the United States Navy.
負責維修，打撈和營救
To repair, to salvage, and to rescue.
有誰不想打仗，現在說還來得及
Anybody doesn't want to go to war, now is the time to say so.
只要你踏上了那艘船 你就是海軍了，朋友
Once you set foot on that boat, you're in the Navy, friend.
我一直想和你談談，邁克
Yeah, I've been meaning to talk with you, Mike.
我老婆的情況不好
My wife's doing poorly.
我希望能再見她一面
I'd like to maybe see her one more time.
你現在可以自由地回家了，梅斯先生
You're free to make your way home any way you can, Mr. Mayes.
他走了誰做飯啊？
Well, if he's leaving, who's gonna cook?
食物中毒是海上人員死亡的最主要原因之一
Food poisoning's one of the leading causes of death at sea.
僅次於安全裝備不足
Right after inadequate safety equipment.
我會做飯，船長，幹了一輩子了
I can cook, Captain. Been doing it all my life.
我不知道，你也厭戰，本傑明
I don't know. You're a little moody for war, Benjamin.
管他呢？
What the hell?
想打倒小日本和匈奴人的都跟我走
I'll take any man wants to kick the shite out of the Japs and the Huns.
就這樣吧，收拾行裝 我們要上戰場了，先生們！
That's it, pack your gear. We're going to war, gentlemen!
她留了紙條
She had left a note.
她寫道，“能遇到你真好”
She wrote, "It was nice to have met you."
就這樣
And that was it.
戰爭和我們想像的不一樣
It wasn't the war any of us expected.
我們只是拖走破損的船 其實都是些廢銅爛鐵
We would just tow crippled ships, scraps of metal, really.
真有戰爭，我們也沒看到
If there was a war, we didn't see it.
派給我們的主炮手非常熱愛海軍
There was a man assigned to us. The Chief Gunner loved the Navy.
最重要的是他愛美國
But most of all, he loved America.
世界上沒有其他國家
There is no other country in the world.
當你拼寫美國…
When you spell America...
他叫鄧尼斯·史密斯 是個純血統的切羅基人 （美洲土著人）
His name was Dennis Smith, and he was a full-blooded Cherokee.
他的家族在美洲居住了500多年
His family had been Americans for over 500 years.
去他們的和平主義者 說什麼不會憑良心打仗
These pacifists. They say they won't fight on conscience.
要是所有人都憑良心
Now, where would be if everybody decided to act
- 那會怎麼樣？ - 冷靜點，長官？
- according to their conscience? - Keep it down, would you, Chief?
嘿，我觀察你很久了
Hey. I've been watching you.
你看上去值得信任
You seem trustworthy.
萬一我有什麼不測
If something happens to me,
你能答應把這個給我老婆嗎？
could you see that this gets to my wife?
他把全部工錢都給了我 一分錢也沒花過
He'd given me all of his pay. Hadn't spent a dime of it.
我希望家人知道，我時刻掛念著他們
I want my family to know I was thinking about them.
全體船員到甲板上！
All hands on deck!
快起來，你們這群懶豬！
Get your asses up here, you lazy bastards!
戰爭終於還是來了
The war had finally found us.
都別動！
All stop!
普萊森特，轉下那燈
Pleasant, man that light.
一艘載有1300人的運輸艦被魚雷擊沉
A transport carrying 1,300 men had been split by a torpedo.
我們是第一個趕到現場的
We were first to arrive at the scene.
- 關掉引擎！ - 都別動！
- Cut the engines! - All stop!
四周只有我們的聲音
We were the only sound.
夥計們！
Fellas!
潛水艇！
Sub!
我們絕對跑不過他們
We sure as hell can't outrun them fuckers.
各就各位！
Battle stations!
謝謝，長官
Thank you, Chief.
什麼？
What?
是最後一個麼？
Is that the last one?
船長！
Captain!
狗日的把我的畫打爛了！
They shot the hell out of my painting!
握著我的手
Give me your other hand.
你會沒事的，船長
You'll be all right, Captain.
天使們在天堂裡 給你留了個好地方呢
They got a nice spot in Heaven waiting for you. Nice spot.
不順心的時候 你可以像瘋狗一樣發狂
You can be as mad as a mad dog at the way things went.
可以破口大駡，詛咒命運
You could swear, curse the Fates.
但到頭來
But when it comes to the end,
還是得放手
you have to let go.
船長？
Captain?
那天，1328人離開了人間
Thirteen hundred and twenty eight men died that day.
我和切羅基人鄧尼斯·史密斯道別
I said my goodbyes to the Cherokee, Dennis Smith.
和約翰·格林道別--他猜得沒錯 他最後還是死在那兒了
John Grimm, who was right, he was gonna die there.
我把普萊森特·柯帝士的錢 寄給了他妻子
I sent Pleasant Curtis' wife his money.
我向雙胞胎的維克·布羅迪道別
I said goodbye to the twin, Vic Brody,
還有邁克·克拉克--切爾西號的船長
and to Mike Clark, captain of the tugboat Chelsea.
我和那些仍舊懷揣夢想的人道別
I said goodbye to all the other men who had dreams of their own,
他們有的想做保險推銷員
all the men who wanted to be insurance salesmen
有的想當醫生，律師 甚至是部落酋長
or doctors or lawyers or Indian chiefs.
這個修不好了
This don't get fixed.
在那兒，死亡不再是自然發生的了
Out here, death didn't seem natural.
我從沒在遠海上見過蜂鳥
I'd never seen a hummingbird that far out to sea.
無論是之前，還是此後
Before or since.
1945年5月，我26歲
And in May of 1945, when I was 26 years old,
我回家了
I came home.
我準備好了！準備好了！
I'm ready! I'm ready!
來了！
I'm coming!
- 我準備好了！ - 這就來了，阿法莉娜
- I'm ready! - All right, I'm coming, Miss Alfalina.
- 奎尼？ - 嗯？
- Queenie? - Yes?
老天爺！你回來了！ 神啊，你回來了！
Sweet Jesus! Oh, you're home! Oh, Lord, you came back!
- 快讓我瞧瞧 - 他是誰呀，媽媽？
- Let me look at you. - Who's that, Mama?
- 孩子啊，這是你哥哥，本傑明 - 我都不知道我還有哥哥
- Child, it's your brother, Benjamin. - I didn't know he was my brother.
你不知道的事情多了去了，小丫頭
There's a shitload of things you don't know, child.
趕緊去把地掃完
Get on out there and finish sweeping.
再把手洗洗來幫我擺餐桌，快去
Come here, wash your hands, help me with the table. Go on, now.
轉過來，你看起來跟重生了一樣！
Turn around. You look like you've been born again.
比春天還有活力！
Younger than the springtime.
要我說，那牧師施法的時候 肯定是又給了你一條命
I think that preacher laid hands on you gave you a second life.
那會我看著你就知道 你跟別人不一樣
I knew it that moment I saw you, you were special.
知道嘛，我的膝蓋現在都酸
I tell you what, my knees are sore,
因為我每天晚上都跪著 求上帝保佑
'cause I've been on them every night asking the Lord,
求他“上帝啊，我只要他平安回家”
I said, "God, just bring him home safely."
還記得我怎麼跟你說的嗎？
Remember what I told you?
“你永遠都猜不到 以後的生活是啥樣子”
"You never know what's coming for you"?
沒錯，快坐下
That's right. Sit down.
這幾年，有碰上什麼有趣兒的事嗎？
Well, you learn anything worth repeating?
- 當然了 - 你嘗過了苦頭
- I sure saw some things. - Oh, you seen some pain.
- 也嘗過甜頭？ - 嗯
- Some joy, too? - Sure. Sure, I did.
我就是想聽你親口說這些 瞧瞧你呀
Yeah, that's what I want to hear. Look at you.
- 蒂奇上哪兒去了？ - 哦，孩子
- Where's Tizzy? - Oh, baby.
韋瑟斯走了，上個月 睡覺的時候去的
Mr. Weathers died in his sleep one night last April.
- 媽媽，您節哀 - 別操心我了，孩子
- Mama, I'm so sorry. - Don't you worry about that, baby.
現在還活著的也就那麼一兩個
Yeah, well, it's only one or two of them left now.
不過都還挺樂呵
They all just about new.
他們應該和別人一樣 也都在等著那一天吧
Guess they're waiting their turn like everybody else, huh?
你能回家陪我，我就知足了！
I'm so glad you're back home with me!
咱得趕緊給你找個媳婦，再找個工作 就這麼定了！
Now, we're gonna have to find you a wife and a new job! That's right.
快進來，幫我擺桌子
Come on in here, help me with this table.
本傑明
Benjamin.
別費勁了，她全聾了
You're wasting your time, baby. She's stone deaf.
你住以前德瑟羅住的房間
Oh, and you'll be staying in what was Mrs. DeSeroux's old room.
你太大個了 再和別人擠一間可不像話
You're too big to be rooming with anybody else.
回家的感覺，很奇妙
It's a funny thing about coming home.
一切看起來都是一樣的 聞起來也是，摸起來也是
Looks the same, smells the same, feels the same.
我說沒說過，我被閃電擊中過七次？
Did I ever tell you I've been struck by lightning seven times?
有一次我就那麼好端端地開著車 心裡想著自己的事
Once when I was sitting in my truck, just minding my own business.
我才意識到，其實變的，只有你自己
You realize what's changed is you.
我回來後不久的某個清晨…
And late one morning, not long after I'd been back...
謝謝
Thank you.
嘿
Hey.
- 請問，奎尼在嗎？ - 黛西？
- Excuse me, is Queenie here? - Daisy?
- 是我啊，本傑明 - 本傑明？
- It's me, Benjamin. - Benjamin?
哦，天！
Oh, my God!
真的是你！本傑明！
Of course it's you! Benjamin!
你過得怎麼樣？ 咱們太久沒見了！
How are you? It's been such a long time.
我有好多事情要問你 你什麼時候回來的？
There's so much I want to know. When did you get back?
我回來也沒幾周
Well, I got back a few weeks ago.
我上次問奎尼，她說你還在打仗 說是在海上的哪兒
I spoke to Queenie, she said you were in the war, somewhere at sea.
- 我們都擔心死你了 - 哦，我挺好的
- We were so, so worried about you. - Oh, I'm okay.
瞧瞧你啊，真是好看
Well, look at you. You're so lovely.
你後來就不給我寫信了
You stopped writing.
“我離開的時候，她還只是個小女孩 如今，卻已出落成了窈窕淑女”
"When I had left, she was a girl. And a woman had taken her place.
“她是我所見過的人中，最美的女子”
"She was the most beautiful woman I'd ever seen."
美
Beautiful.
是“最美”
"The most beautiful."
- 你還記得富勒奶奶嗎？ - 當然了，怎麼了？
- You remember Grandma Fuller? - Why, sure I do.
- 她過世了 - 我聽說了，節哀
- She passed. - I heard that. I'm sorry.
真不敢想，我們又見面了 這一定是緣分
I just can't believe we're both here. Must be fate.
不對不對，他們管這叫什麼來著？
No, no, what do they call it?
天意
Kismet.
你知道愛德格·西嗎？ 就是那個會通靈的？
Do you know about Edgar Cayce, the psychic?
應該沒…
I don't believe I...
他說，萬事萬物都是註定的
He says that everything is predetermined,
不過我寧願把這當成緣分
but I like to think of it as fate.
雖然也搞不懂這到底是怎麼回事 我還是很高興咱們重逢了
I'm not sure how it works, but I'm glad it happened.
你去過曼哈頓嗎？ 就在我住的地方河對面
Have you been to Manhattan? It's right across the river from me.
要是我站在床上
Now, I can see the Empire State Building
就可以望見帝國大廈
if I stand on my bed.
說說你吧？你都去哪了？
What about you? Where have you been?
全都告訴我，上次你寫信說 你去俄國了
Tell me everything. Last time you wrote, you said you'd been to Russia.
我一直想去那呢 那兒真像別人說的那麼冷嗎？
I've always wanted to go to Russia. Is it as cold as they say?
- 冷多了 - 我的天呀
- Twice as cold. - My goodness.
大家嘴上都說你不一樣 我可是真的覺得你不是一般人
We always said you were different. But I think you really are.
你還說你遇上了你喜歡的人 最後有結果嗎？
You wrote that you met somebody. Did it work out?
還是沒成
It ran its course.
嘿，還記得這個嗎？
Hey, do you remember this?
“照片裡畫的是大袋鼠
"This is the picture of Old Man Kangaroo
下午五點，他終於會蹦蹦跳了”
"at 5:00 in the afternoon."
一起吃個晚飯好嗎？
Would you like to have dinner?
我有沒有跟你說過 我跟著巴蘭欽跳舞呀？ （著名芭蕾舞導演）
Did I tell you that I danced for Balanchine?
他可是個有名的編舞大師 他說我的線條很完美
Oh, he's a famous choreographer. He said that I had perfect line.
知道嗎，有一個排練，有人摔倒
You know, in a rehearsal once, a dancer fell.
然後他…就把這個動作 編進舞蹈裡去了！
And he just... He just put it right into the production.
你能想像那情形嗎？ 在一部…經典芭蕾舞劇裡
I mean, can you imagine that? Like in a... In a classical ballet?
讓一個演員，故意跌倒
You know, a dancer, intentionally falling.
如今形容舞蹈有個新詞了 叫“抽象”
There's a whole new word for dance now. It's called "abstract."
當然了，有名的大師不止他一個
No, he's not the only one, though.
還有林肯·柯爾斯坦 露西亞·切斯，哦，對…
There's Lincoln Kirstein and Lucia Chase, and oh, my...
還有阿格尼·德·米爾
Oh, there's Agnes de Mille.
她根本就不管什麼條條框框
She's just torn up all those conventions,
就是“抬頭挺胸”那一套
you know, all that straight-up-and-down stuff.
她說舞蹈最重要的不是形式 而是舞者的感覺
It's not about the formality of the dance, it's about what the dancer's feeling.
她跟我說的這些 就像是另一個全新的世界
As she told me about this big new world,
那些名字，對我來說，啥也不是
names that didn't mean a thing to me,
其實她說什麼，我也沒怎麼聽進去
I didn't really hear very much of what she was saying.
一切都是全新的，現代的，美式的！
It's new and it's modern and it's American.
只有他們瞭解我們的活力和形體
They understand our vigor and our physicality.
哦，天，我是不是說太多了呀
Oh, my God. I've just been talking and talking.
沒有沒有，我喜歡聽你講 我不知道你還抽煙
No, no, I've enjoyed listening. I didn't know you smoked.
我夠大了
I'm old enough.
除了這個，還能做很多別的
I'm old enough for a lot of things.
在紐約那會，我們整晚刷夜
In New York, we stay up all night,
然後看著太陽爬上倉庫屋頂
watch the sun come up over the warehouses.
在那兒，總是有新鮮事可做
There's always something to do.
明天我就得回去了
I have to go back tomorrow.
- 這麼快 - 真想留下來
- So soon. - Wish I could stay.
如今，跳舞的人 都不需要服裝和背景了
Dancers don't need costumes or scenery anymore.
我都能想像 自己不穿衣服跳舞的樣子
I can imagine dancing completely naked.
你讀過D.H.勞倫斯的書嗎？
Have you read D.H. Lawrence?
- 呃… - 他的書都被禁了
- Well... - His books were banned.
那些文字，讀起來，就像做愛
The words are like making love.
在舞團，大家必須互相信任
In our company, we have to trust each other.
性，就是條件之一
Sex is a part of it.
知道嘛，很多跳舞的都是女同
You know, a lot of the dancers are lesbians.
有一個女人，就想跟我睡
There was one woman who wanted to sleep with me.
- 你聽了會不高興嗎？ - 關於哪部分？
- Does that upset you? - Which part?
就是有人想和我睡那部分
Somebody wanting to sleep with me.
你很性感
You're a desirable woman.
我想，他們很多人都會想和你睡吧
I would think most of them would want to sleep with you.
咱們回去吧
Let's go back to the house.
或者到哪開間房
Or we could get a room somewhere.
- 你可以脫下夾克… - 這樣似乎不好，黛西
- We could lay down your jacket. - I don't know, Daisy.
也不是說我不想還是怎麼的 我只是怕，會讓你失望
It's not that I wouldn't like to or anything. I think I'll just disappoint you.
本傑明，我和更老的人都在一起過
Oh, Benjamin, I've been with older men.
明早你就要回紐約了
You're going back to New York in the morning.
你該和朋友在一起
You should be with your friends.
- 你只能年輕一次 - 我夠大了
- You're only young once. - Oh, I'm old enough.
黛西，就是，今晚不行
Daisy, just not tonight, is all.
我們可以去聽聽音樂
We could go hear some music.
我們的生命，因為各種各樣的機遇 而變得更有意義
Our lives are defined by opportunities.
甚至那些我們錯過的
Even the ones we miss.
你看起來，如此英俊，與眾不同
You look so handsome and so distinguished.
據說颶風不會過來 剛好從我們這塊刮過去
They're saying the hurricane's gonna miss us, blow right on by.
- 太好了 - 我在毯子下面和媽媽一起躺著
- Oh, that's great. - I'll stay under the blankets with Mother.
她什麼也沒說…本傑明你在嗎？
She says nothing... Benjamin?
“我的生命…
"Things were becoming different..."
又有了不一樣的變化
... for me.
我的頭髮，越來越黑，像野草一樣生長
My hair had very little gray and grew like weeds.
我的嗅覺更加靈敏 聽覺，也加更敏銳
My sense of smell was keener. My hearing, more acute.
我走得更快更遠
I could walk further and faster.
別人都在變老 而我，卻獨自一人，越來越年輕
While everybody else was aging, I was getting younger, all alone.
進來吧
Come in.
本傑明
Benjamin.
- 還記得我嗎？ - 當然了，巴頓先生
- Do you remember me? - Well, sure I do, Mr. Button.
- 你這是怎麼了？ - 該死的腳，感染了，那個…
- What happened to you? - Darn foot. Got infected, so...
歡迎回家，朋友
Welcome home, my friend.
你還是喜歡把威士卡 和別的酒混起來喝啊
I see you're still drinking your Sazerac with whiskey.
呵，習慣這東西
Creature of habit.
你還常去波旁大道那邊的工廠嗎？
You still visiting the house on Bourbon Street?
很久沒去了
Not for a long time.
說來有趣
Interesting times, though.
我們一開始每天做四萬個紐扣 到後來一天50萬
We went from making 40,000 to nearly half a million buttons a day.
廠裡的工人多了十倍
We employed 10 times the number of people.
我們沒日沒夜地工作
We were operating around the clock.
說來慚愧
Damn shame.
戰爭讓紐扣生意更紅火了
The war has been kind to the button industry.
知道嘛
You know,
我病了，不知道還能活多久
I'm sick. I don't know how much longer I have.
- 您也別太難過了，巴頓先生 - 別這麼說…
- I'm sorry to hear that, Mr. Button. - No...
我沒什麼朋友，一直都是獨來獨往
I don't have any people. I keep to myself.
但願你不要介意，不過，如果有可能
I hope you don't mind, but, whenever possible,
我希望你可以多陪陪我
I'd enjoy your company.
如果力所能及，我當然會的
I'll certainly do what I can.
本傑明，你懂紐扣生意嗎？
Benjamin, do you know anything about buttons?
到現在，巴頓紐扣廠已經 在家族中傳承了124年了
Now, Button's Buttons has been in our family for 124 years.
我的祖父是個裁縫 只在里士滿開了間小裁縫鋪
My grandfather was a tailor, and he had a small shop in Richmond.
內戰過後，他搬到了新奧爾良
After the Civil War, he moved to New Orleans,
在那兒，我父親奮發圖強 開始經營自己的紐扣生意
where my father had the wisdom to make our own buttons.
於是，在他的大力改革下 小裁縫鋪成長到了今天這樣的規模
So, with his help, the tailor shop grew to this.
如今，我卻連衣服都不會自己縫了
And today, I can't sew a stitch.
這故事真的很有意思
That's very, very interesting.
很顯然，您自己幹得也不錯嘛
You sure have done well for yourself.
那我能幫上什麼忙呢，巴頓先生？
So, what can I do for you, Mr. Button?
本傑明，你是我兒子
Benjamin? You're my son.
抱歉，我以前從沒提起過
I'm so sorry I never told you before.
你是大戰結束那晚出生的
You were born the night the Great War ended.
你母親難產而死
Your mother died giving birth to you.
我以為你是怪物
I thought you were a monster.
我向你母親保證過 保證你會平平安安
I promised your mother I'd make sure you were safe.
對不起，我不該拋棄你
I should never have abandoned you.
我母親？
My mother?
龐恰特雷恩湖邊的避暑別墅
At the summer house on Lake Pontchartrain.
我小時候，總喜歡比大家早起
When I was a boy, I'd love to wake up before anyone else,
然後跑到湖邊，迎接新一天的開始
run down to that lake and watch the day begin.
那時候，我覺得自己 好像是這世上唯一一個活人
It was as if I was the only one alive.
第一眼看到她，我就愛上她了
I fell in love the first time I saw her.
你母親叫卡洛琳·墨菲
Your mother's name was Caroline Murphy.
她在你爺爺的廚房裡幹活
She worked in your grandfather's kitchen.
她是都柏林人
She's from Dublin.
1903年，她和她的兄弟姐妹 就到美國來謀生了
In 1903, Caroline and all her brothers and sisters came to live here,
就住在新奧爾良
in New Orleans.
我常常找藉口下廚房
I'd find excuses to go down to that kitchen
就為了看她一眼
just so I could look at her.
1918年4月25號，那天 是我一生中最快樂的時光
April 25th, 1918. Happiest day of my life.
那天，我迎娶了你母親
The day I married your mother.
你為什麼不早點告訴我？
Why didn't you just tell me?
我準備把遺產都留給你
I plan on leaving everything I have to you.
- 我該走了 - 去哪？
- I have to go. - Where?
回家
Home.
他怎麼想的，嗯？
And what does he think, anyway?
他以為自己這麼冒出來
He thinks he can just show up
然後就沒事了？
and everything's supposed to be fine and dandy.
然後大家就能做朋友了？
Everybody's just supposed to be friends.
要我說，這事我跟他沒完
Well, he got another thing coming, that's for sure.
老天有眼，我跟他沒完！
God be my witness, he got another thing coming.
他丟掉你那晚，只留了18塊錢
He left us $18 that night you was found.
18張皺巴巴的票子！
Eighteen ratty dollars
- 還有一塊髒兮兮的尿布 - 晚安了，媽
- and a filthy diaper. - Good night, Mama.
晚安，寶貝兒
Good night, baby.
我有沒有跟你說過 我被閃電擊中過七次？
Did I ever tell you I was struck by lightning seven times?
有一次，我就那麼好好得遛著狗
Once, I was walking my dog down the road.
現在我瞎了一隻眼，幾乎聽不見
I'm blind in the one eye, can't hardly hear,
還無緣無故抽搐發抖，老是忘東西
get twitches and shakes out of nowhere, always losing my line of thought.
但你知道嘛？
But you know what?
老天爺總是不斷地提醒我 讓我知道自己還活著，有多幸運
God keeps reminding me I'm lucky to be alive.
暴風雨快來了
Storm's coming.
可以為您效勞嗎？ 樓上，第一間臥室
May I help you, sir? Up the stairs, first bedroom.
謝謝
Thank you.
醒醒
Wake up.
我來幫你穿上衣服
Let's get you dressed.
對，就這樣
Now that's something.
謝謝
Thank you.
不順心的時候 你可以像瘋狗那樣發狂
You can be mad as a mad dog at the way things went.
你可以破口大駡，詛咒命運
You can swear and curse the Fates.
但到頭來
But when it comes to the end,
還是得放手
you have to let go.
這葬禮很體面
Well, it sure is a beautiful service.
他會葬在你母親旁邊
He'll be buried right next to your mother.
您就是我母親
You're my mother.
我的孩子
My baby.
我以前還從沒來過紐約
Now, I'd never seen New York.
- 打擾下，我是黛西的朋友 - 這邊
- Excuse me, I'm a friend of Daisy's. - Right this way.
- 黛西有人找，黛西！ - 來了！
- Daisy has company. Daisy! Daisy! - Yes!
- 我們要放衣服 - 是誰找我呀？
- We need the wardrobe. - Is somebody looking for me?
- 本傑明 - 嗨
- Benjamin. - Hi.
- 你來這做什麼？ - 我覺得應該來看看你
- What are you doing here? - Thought I'd come visit.
要是可以，約你出去轉轉
Spend some time with you, if I could.
真希望你事先給我個電話 這樣我都沒法準備
Oh, well, I wish you would've called. You took me by surprise.
- 要是不喜歡就扔了吧 - 哪裡，謝了，花很好看
- You can just throw them out. - No. Thank you, they're lovely.
我從頭到尾都在看你 你真是…太迷人了
I couldn't take my eyes off of you. I thought you were mesmerizing.
謝謝，謝謝你這麼說
Thank you. That's very kind of you to say.
我得去換身衣服了 我們幾個要去聚會下
I better get changed. A group of us are going to a party.
- 你來嗎？ - 聽人說有家餐館不錯
- Would you want to come? - Someone told me about a restaurant
你應該也會喜歡
I thought you might enjoy.
我定了位，算是以防萬一
I made a reservation, just in case.
不過我們跳完舞之後都會聚聚…
Just, all the dancers go out after the show. You're...
你來我們會很歡迎的 我去換衣服，好嗎？
You're welcome to come with us. I'll get changed. All right?
她還給俄羅斯芭蕾舞團排過舞
She choreographs for the Ballets Russes.
太神了
She's divine.
你真美
You were breathtaking.
小甜心
Sweetie.
這是大衛，他也是舞團的
This is David. He dances with the company.
- 這是本傑明 - 誰？
- This is Benjamin. - Who?
- 我跟你說起過他的 - 哦，是你啊，近來可好啊
- I told you about him. - Oh, yeah. How you doing?
- 我去給你拿杯喝的 - 嗯，謝了
- I'll go get you a drink. - All right. Thanks.
這麼說，你是她奶奶的朋友？
So, you were a friend of her grandmother's?
還是就那一類的？
Or something like that?
差不多吧
Something like that.
嘿，失陪
Hey, excuse me.
來吧
Come on.
嘿！
Hey!
我真不知道你會來
Now, I had no idea you were coming.
天啊，本傑明
Lord, Benjamin.
你想要我怎樣呢？ 難道要我丟下這一切，跟你走嗎？
What did you expect? What, you want me to drop everything?
這可是我的人生
Now, this is my life.
寶貝兒，去市中心不？
Babe! You going downtown?
來吧，你也會玩得很開心的
Come on. You'll have a good time.
那兒有很多音樂家和有趣的人
There's lots of musicians, interesting people.
真的不用了，都是我不好
You don't have to do that. This is my fault.
我是該先打個電話
I should've called.
我本以為我突然過來
I thought I'd come here
會給你一個大驚喜
and sweep you off your feet or something.
- 黛西，快來吧，出發了！ - 馬上到
- Daisy! Come on! Let's go. - Be right there.
他看來還不錯
Seems nice.
你愛他嗎？
Do you love him?
應該吧
I think so.
真替你高興
I'm happy for you.
那老家見吧
Maybe I'll see you at home.
好吧
Okay.
我很喜歡你的演出！
I enjoyed the show!
他來，是想告訴我，他父親死了
He came to tell me his father had died.
- 你也猜不到啊 - 我那時才23歲，我…只是不在乎這些
- You couldn't have known. - I was 23. I... I just didn't care.
那你後來呢？
What did you do next?
有些照片，我記得 就放在包的前袋裡
Some photographs, I think, in the front of my bag.
我那會還挺了不得
I was as good a dancer as I was ever gonna be.
有那麼五年，我…
For five years, I...
在世界各地表演
I danced everywhere.
倫敦，維也納，布拉格
London, Vienna, Prague.
我從沒見過這些照片
I've never seen these.
媽
Mom.
你從來沒提你跳舞的事
You never talked about your dancing.
我還是頭一個
Well, I was the only American
受邀，和大劇院舞團共舞的美國人 （Bolshoi：俄國著名芭蕾舞團）
to be invited to dance with the Bolshoi, sugar.
那真是太棒了
It was glorious.
但我從沒忘記本傑明
But Benjamin was never far from my thoughts.
有時候，我會不自覺地說…
And I'd find myself saying...
晚安，本傑明
Good night, Benjamin.
- “晚安，黛西” - 他也這麼說？
- "Good night, Daisy." - He said that?
“生活並沒有那麼複雜
"Life wasn't all that complicated.
要是你喜歡 大可以說我是在探索生命”
"If you want, you might say I was looking for something."
本傑明，拉·圖爾諾夫人剛剛過世了
Benjamin? Mrs. La Tourneau just passed.
- 本傑明·巴頓先生的信 - 我就是
- Letter for Mr. Benjamin Button? - That'd be me.
謝謝
Thank you.
我找黛西·富勒小姐
Miss Daisy Fuller.
- 稍等，請先坐一會 - 好的
- Just a minute. Please have a seat. - Sure.
有時候，我們的人生軌道 會與別人的交錯，只是不自知罷了
Sometimes we're on a collision course and we just don't know it.
無論是意外，還是天意 我們都無力改變
Whether it's by accident or by design, there's not a thing we can do about it.
巴黎，一名女子正要出門購物
A woman in Paris was on her way to go shopping.
卻發現忘帶外套，於是回家去取
But she had forgotten her coat, went back to get it.
她拿起外套，電話鈴響
When she had gotten her coat, the phone had rung.
她接起電話，聊了一會
So she had stopped to answer it and talked for a couple of minutes.
與此同時
While the woman was on the phone,
黛西正為一場巴黎歌劇院的演出彩排
Daisy was rehearsing for a performance at the Paris Opera House.
不久，女子聊完，掛了電話
And while she was rehearsing, the woman, off the phone now,
下樓去招計程車
had gone outside to get a taxi.
另一邊，計程車司機 剛剛送完一位客人
Now, a taxi driver had dropped off a fare earlier,
便停了車，去買咖啡
and had stopped to get a cup of coffee.
而黛西還在繼續排練
And all the while, Daisy was rehearsing.
那位送完了客人
And this cab driver, who dropped off the earlier fare
便去買咖啡的司機
and had stopped to get the cup of coffee,
正巧接了要去購物的那位女子
he picked up the lady who was going shopping
而那位女子，因為一番延誤 剛錯過了之前的車
and had missed getting the earlier cab.
車子中途停了一下 因為有人橫穿馬路
The taxi had to stop for a man crossing the street,
這位男子那天比平時晚起了五分鐘
who had left for work five minutes later than he normally did
因為他忘了定鬧鐘
because he forgot to set his alarm.
那個沒定鬧鐘，早上遲到的人 橫穿馬路的時候
While that man, late for work, was crossing the street,
黛西已經排練結束，開始沖澡
Daisy had finished rehearsing and was taking a shower.
她在洗澡的時候
And while Daisy was showering,
計程車停在一家糖果店門口 等女客人去取包裹
the taxi was waiting outside a boutique for the woman to pick up a package
可包裹還沒備好
which hadn't been wrapped yet,
因為打包的女孩
because the girl who was supposed to wrap it
昨晚剛剛與男友分手 太過傷心而忘了打包
had broken up with her boyfriend the night before and forgot.
包裹打好之後，女子回到車上
When the package was wrapped, the woman, who was back in the cab,
又被一輛貨車擋住了去路
was blocked by a delivery truck.
與此同時，黛西換上了衣服
All the while, Daisy was getting dressed.
貨車開走之後，出租才重新上路
The delivery truck pulled away, and the taxi was able to move
而黛西最後一個才穿好衣服
while Daisy, the last to be dressed,
又等了一會斷了鞋帶的朋友
waited for one of her friends who had broken a shoelace.
出租在路燈處停下時
While the taxi was stopped, waiting for a traffic light,
黛西和她朋友正從劇場後門出來
Daisy and her friend came out the back of the theater.
如果有一件事，有一點點不一樣
And if only one thing had happened differently,
如果那鞋帶沒斷
if that shoelace hadn't broken
如果那貨車早一點兒開走
or that delivery truck had moved moments earlier
或者包裹早早備好
or that package had been wrapped and ready
因為男孩沒和女孩分手
because the girl hadn't broken up with her boyfriend,
又或者那男子定了鬧鐘 和平時一樣起床
or that man had set his alarm and got up five minutes earlier
再或者司機沒有停車喝咖啡
or that taxi driver hadn't stopped for a cup of coffee
而那女子也帶了外套 上了之前的出租
or that woman had remembered her coat and got into an earlier cab,
那麼，黛西和她朋友 就會平平安安地穿過馬路
Daisy and her friend would have crossed the street
那出租也只是和她們擦身而過
and the taxi would have driven by.
但是，生活沒有如果
But, life being what it is,
只有一連串互相交錯的意外
a series of intersecting lives and incidents
無人能夠控制
out of anyone's control,
那輛出租沒有和她們擦身而過
that taxi did not go by,
而就在那時，司機分了一下神
and that driver was momentarily distracted.
黛西！
Daisy!
車子撞倒了黛西
And that taxi hit Daisy.
黛西！來人啊！
Daisy! Help!
她的腿，就被撞斷了
And her leg was crushed.
黛西？
Daisy?
- 誰讓你來的？ - 你朋友寫信給我
- Who told you? - Your friend wired me.
你這麼大老遠來看我，真是好心
Very kind of you to come all this way to see that I was all right.
換了是你，也會這麼做的
You'd do the same for me.
我的天
My God.
瞧瞧你，你太完美了
Look at you. You're perfect.
真希望你沒來這 我不想你看到我這樣子
I wish you hadn't come here. I don't want you to see me like this.
她的腿，斷成了五段
Her leg had been broken in five places.
如果治療得當，假以時日 她或許還能重新走路
And with therapy and time, she might walk again.
但不可能再跳舞了
But she'd never dance.
我帶你回家
I'm gonna take you home with me.
- 我願意照顧你 - 我不回新奧爾良
- I want to look after you. - I'm not going back to New Orleans.
那我就留在巴黎陪你
Then I'll stay here in Paris.
你還不明白嗎？我不用你可憐我！
Don't you understand? I don't want your help.
我現在是很難過，可也不用你陪
I know I'm feeling sorry for myself, but I don't want to be with you.
在紐約那會就想告訴你了 可你就是不聽
Tried to tell you that in New York. You don't listen.
你或許會改變主意
You might change your mind.
你也不是小孩子了，本傑明
We are not little children anymore, Benjamin.
拜託，從我的生命裡消失吧
Just stay out of my life.
我真的是太狠心了
I was awfully cruel.
他一定不明白 我只是不想讓他看我那副樣子
He didn't understand. I couldn't have him see me like that.
“我沒有馬上離開
"I didn't leave right away.
而是在巴黎逗留了一陣子 暗中照看她”
"I stayed in Paris for a while to look out for her."
我一點也不知道
I never knew that.
哦，親愛的，能幫我叫下護士嗎？
Oh, darling, could you get the nurse?
我又重新學會走路
I taught myself to walk again.
又坐火車去盧德（法國西南部小城）
I took the train to Lourdes.
我看看，很正常，脈搏舒緩下來了
Let's take a look. That's normal. Pulse rate is slowing.
稍後可能會呼吸困難一會
She is gonna struggle to breathe.
- 你在這沒事吧？ - 嗯
- Will you be all right? - Yeah.
我接著讀，他說“我回到家” 這裡有很多頁被撕掉了
All right, he says, "I went back home." And then there's a lot of pages torn out.
“我聆聽著房子的低語” 我讀過這段了
"I listened to the sound of the house." I read that already.
他…
He...
他把什麼東西濺到紙上 這段看不清了，媽
He spilt something on it, so it's hard to read, Mom.
好像是關於帆船的 您知道他在說什麼嗎？
Something about sailing, does that make sense?
我用父親留在湖邊別墅的帆船 學會了駕駛
I learned to sail an old boat of my father's from the lake house.
說老實話
I can't lie.
我也確實很享受 與一兩位女子共度的時光
I did enjoy the company of a woman or two.
也許是三個吧
Or maybe three.
何必這麼煩呢，山姆 反正明天還是要去一趟的
Don't know why you bother, Sam, just gonna be there again tomorrow.
媽媽
Mama.
1962年春天
And in the spring of 1962,
她回來了
she came back.
- 想知道我去了哪兒嗎？ - 不想
- You want to know where I've been? - No.
你怎麼連封信也不寫？ 就那麼人間蒸發了一樣
How come you didn't write or nothing? Just disappearing like that.
我只是去處理了一下私事
It was something I needed to do for myself.
我也從沒覺得你自私
Yeah, well, I never took you to be the selfish type.
但願如此
I sure hope I'm not wrong.
我一般看人不會看走眼的
I'm usually not wrong about people.
- 晚安，媽媽 - 晚安，寶貝兒
- Good night, Mama. - Good night, baby.
你倆好好玩吧
Y'all have fun.
- 你說到現在，還沒哪句話多過兩個字呢 - 我只是不想破壞氣氛
- You haven't said two words. - I don't want to ruin it.
- 和我睡吧 - 絕對地
- Sleep with me? - Absolutely.
我邀她與我出遊
I asked her to come away with me.
我們沿著佛羅里達群島 一路乘帆駛進海灣
We sailed into the Gulf along the Florida Keys.
真高興我不是26歲那年和你在一起
I am so glad we didn't find one another when I was 26.
- 這話怎麼說？ - 我那會太嫩了
- Why do you say that? - I was so young.
你又太老
And you were so old.
現在這樣，才最自然
It happened when it was supposed to happen.
和你在一起的每分每秒，我都會珍惜
I will enjoy each and every moment I have with you.
我跟你打賭，我在這能比你堅持更久
I bet I can stay out here longer than you.
那我賭你撐不了
I bet you can't.
你臉上幾乎沒有皺紋
Barely a line or a crease.
而我，每天都會多長出幾條，不公平
Every day I have more wrinkles. It's not fair.
我喜歡你的皺紋，每一條都愛
I love your wrinkles. Both of them.
越活越年輕是種什麼感覺？
What's it like growing younger?
還真是很難形容 我自己又沒法看到全部變化
I can't really say. I'm always looking out my own eyes.
我要是成了黃臉婆，你還會愛我嗎？
Will you still love me when my skin grows old and saggy?
等我老到臉上長滿青春痘，老到尿床
Will you still love me when I have acne? When I wet the bed?
老到連樓梯下有什麼都怕 你還會愛我嗎？
When I'm afraid of what's under the stairs?
怎麼了？
What?
- 你在想什麼？ - 我在想，為什麼世上沒有永恆呢
- What are you thinking? - Well, I was thinking how nothing lasts.
多可惜
And what a shame that is.
有些事情，是永恆的
Some things last.
- 晚安，黛西 - 晚安，本傑明
- Good night, Daisy. - Good night, Benjamin.
媽？
Mom?
- 你什麼時候認識爸爸的？ - 在那之後
- When did you meet Dad? - Some time after that.
- 你跟他說過這個本傑明的事嗎？ - 親愛的，他知道得不少
- Did you tell him about this Benjamin? - He knew enough, darling.
媽？
Mama?
奎尼？
Queenie?
是誰啊？
Hello?
哦，嗨，卡特夫人，大家都上哪去了？
Oh, hi, Mrs. Carter, it's Benjamin. Where is everybody?
哦，本傑明，奎尼去世了，節哀啊
Oh, Benjamin. Queenie died. I'm so sorry.
你失去親人，我也很難過 她是個好女人
I'm so sorry for your loss. She was a great woman.
我們深表哀悼
Our deepest condolences.
她葬在她的摯愛，韋瑟斯身邊
We buried her beside her beloved Mr. Weathers.
為了過上我們自己的生活
And so we might have memories of our own,
我賣了父親的房子
we sold my father's house on Esplanade.
親愛的，這老房子真是太棒了！
It is a wonderful old place, darling.
我想我們生活在這裡會很開心
I think we are going to be so happy here.
哦，好長的家族史啊
Oh, what a long family history you have.
和房子的歷史一樣長
They come with the house.
- 上來吧 - 你一定得看看主臥室
- Come on. - You have to see the master suite.
我們買了一套二聯式的小公寓
We bought ourselves a duplex.
我愛死那房子了
I loved that house.
有木柴的味道
It smelled like firewood.
別…別停下，親愛的
Don't... Don't stop, darling.
“那是我生命中最快樂的時光”
"It was one of the happiest times of my life."
我們半件傢俱也沒有
We didn't have a stick of furniture.
在起居室裡野餐
We would have picnics in the living room.
想什麼時候吃飯就什麼時候吃 只要願意，就通宵不睡
We ate when we felt like it. Stayed up all night when we wanted.
我們發誓，一定不過循規蹈矩的生活
We vowed never to fall into routine,
絕不按時上床，起床
to go to bed or wake up at the same time.
我們就在床墊上過活
We lived on that mattress.
我們的鄰居，凡·丹夫人，是個理療師
Our neighbor, a Mrs. Van Dam, was a physical therapist.
離家四個街區，就有個公共泳池
We lived four blocks from a public pool.
也許，你能多跳幾年舞
You know, you might've got a few more years out of it,
可你的事業太與眾不同
but you chose to do something so special and unique
只有幾年的黃金時間可以發展
that there was only a short window of time you could do it.
就算沒發生意外
So, even if nothing ever happened,
你現在還是會回來，在這
you'd still be right here where you are now.
我只是不喜歡變老
I just don't like getting old.
這裡的水消毒過頭了 （泳池用氯氣消毒，氯氣有強刺激性）
They put too much chlorine in here.
我保證，以後再也不會自怨自艾了
I promise you I'll never lose myself to self-pity again.
那時候，我知道
And I think right there and then
她懂了，沒人是永遠完美無瑕的
she realized none of us is perfect forever.
她的內心，終於平靜了
She found peace.
她辦了間舞蹈室，教小女孩跳舞
She opened a studio and taught young girls how to dance.
足尖點地
And tendu.
跳回來，點地，點地，點地 好極了！
Come back the other way. And spot, spot, spot. Excellent.
- 晚安，黛西老師 - 晚安
- Good night, Miss Daisy. - Good night.
你看起來真美
You certainly are beautiful to watch.
舞蹈好不好就看身線
Dancing's all about the line.
身體的曲線
The line of your body.
早晚，身線都有不好的一天 之後，就一去不復返了
Sooner or later, you lose that line, and you never get it back.
我算了下，你是1918年出生的 今年也49了
I figure, you were born in 1918, 49 years ago.
我43
I'm 43.
差不多算是同齡
We are almost the same age.
- 我們在人生的中點相遇 - 總算是遇上了
- We're meeting in the middle. - We finally caught up with each other.
等下
Wait.
我想記著我們現在的樣子
I want to remember us just as we are now.
我有了
I'm pregnant.
知道嘛，我敢打賭 那護士說漏過嘴，是男孩
You know, I swear the nurse slipped and said it was a boy.
可我覺得是女孩
But I think it's a girl.
- 我知道你擔心 - 我也沒藏著掖著
- I know you're afraid. - I'm not hiding it.
好吧
Okay.
- 你最擔心什麼？ - 孩子像我
- What's your worst fear? - Baby born like me.
那我更愛他還來不及呢
Then I will love it all the more.
這麼說吧，我這樣越活越小 怎麼能當好一個父親？
Okay. How can I be a father when I'm heading in the other direction?
對孩子來說也不公平，我不想變成累贅
It's not fair to a child. I don't want to be anybody's burden.
甜心，到頭來 我們都會重新用上尿布
Sugar, we all end up in diapers.
我會想辦法，讓一切都順利
I am gonna make this work.
我想要這孩子，我想和你一起 把他養育成人
I want this, and I want it with you.
你想要什麼，我就儘量給你 無論有多難
I want you to have everything you want, all of it.
只是現在，我還沒想好 我這樣子，怎麼才能不影響到孩子
I'm just not sure how to reconcile this.
你會跟一個盲人說，他不能有孩子嗎？
Would you tell a blind man he couldn't have children?
打包好了
Here you go.
你是孩子的父親，能當多久當多久
You'll be a father for as long as you can.
我知道最後會是什麼結局 我也準備好面對了
I know the consequences. I've accepted that.
為了愛你，我可以不惜一切
Loving you is worth everything to me.
我要噓噓去
I have to go pee.
有史以來，橫渡英吉利海峽 最年長的婦女
The oldest woman to ever swim the English Channel
今日遊抵加來…
arrived here today in Calais...
- 不用找了 - 全程花去34小時
- Keep it. - ... having made the swim in 34 hours,
22分鐘，14秒
22 minutes and 14 seconds.
現年68歲的伊莉莎白·亞伯特 于格林尼治時間5:38抵岸
The 68-year-old Elizabeth Abbott arrived at 5:38 Greenwich mean time,
雖然精疲力竭，但還是笑顏逐開
exhausted but happy.
亞伯特女士，能用幾句話來概括 形容下您的此次壯舉嗎？
Miss Abbott, how would you sum up, in words, this achievement?
那我得說…
I suppose...
凡事皆有可能
Anything's possible.
- 夠了嗎？ - 嗯，非常感謝
- All right? - Yes. Thank you.
- 可以走了嗎？ - 真謝謝你
- You ready? - Thank you very much.
謝謝大家
Thank you. Thank you all.
- 嗯 - 你們真好
- Yeah. - You're very kind.
春天裡的某一天，尋常的一天…
In the spring, on a day like any other...
我出門去，一小時就回來！
I'll be back in an hour!
親愛的？
Honey?
快叫救護車！
Go and call an ambulance!
快生了
The baby's coming.
接線員，我找救護車
Operator, I need an ambulance.
- 快生了！ - 拿破崙路2714號
- The baby's coming! - 2714 Napoleon.
就這樣，注意呼吸
There you go. Keep breathing.
深呼吸，用力！
Deep breaths. Push.
就這樣
There we go.
母女平安，孩子很健康
Everyone's fine. She's a perfectly healthy baby girl.
親愛的？
Honey?
她生下了一個5磅4盎司重的女孩 （約6斤3兩）
She gave birth to a five pound, four ounce baby girl.
你數過腳趾了嗎？
Did you count the toes?
她可真漂亮
She's perfect.
“我們用我母親的名字 給她取名，卡洛琳”
"And we named her for my mother, Caroline."
這個叫本傑明的，是我父親？
This Benjamin was my father?
你就這麼告訴我真相？
And this is how you tell me?
我走開一會
Excuse me.
一場特大颶風所需具備的條件 都已成形
... because all the ingredients are there for a major storm,
本次颶風甚至可能達到第5級 （約相當於16級颱風）
possibly even up to a Category 5.
嘿，我知道你不好受 可不能在這吸煙
Hey, I know it's hard. You can't smoke in here.
目前還不知其登陸地點
Nobody can tell you exactly where it's gonna hit,
但我們會儘快查閱已有資料
but we have to go with the guidance that we have,
重新整理，並為大家 提供相應的防颱措施
incorporate that information and then pass it along to you.
“醫生說得沒錯，你慢慢長大 正常，健康”
"You grew as the doctor had promised, normal and healthy."
你該給她找個能勝任的父親
You're gonna have to find a real father for her.
你說什麼呀
What are you talking about?
得有人陪著她長大
She's gonna need someone to grow old with.
她會學著接受這一切的 再說，她愛你
She'll learn to accept whatever happens. She loves you.
親愛的，她需要的是父親，不是玩伴
Honey, she needs a father, not a playmate.
- 是我的問題嗎？ - 當然不是
- Is it me? - Of course not.
- 是不是我變老了，惹你嫌了？ - 當然不是
- Is my age beginning to bother you? - Of course not.
- 你是不是就這個意思？ - 你沒法把我們兩個一起養
- Is that what you're telling me? - You can't raise the both of us.
今天是你的第一次生日 我們為你辦了場生日聚會
It was your first birthday. We had a party for you.
屋子裡全是小朋友
The house was filled with children.
- 近來如何啊？ - 嘿，老兄
- How are you? - Hey, man.
一眨眼的功夫 他們就該上高中，開始約會了
Before you turn around, they'll be in high school, dating.
我賣了龐恰特雷恩湖邊的避暑別墅
I sold the summer house on Lake Pontchartrain,
賣了巴頓紐扣廠
I sold Button's Buttons,
賣了父親的帆船，把錢全都存進了銀行
I sold my father's sailboat, put it all into a savings account.
這樣你和你媽媽或許能過上好日子
And so that you and your mother might have a life,
趁你還不記得我，我得早日離開
I left, before you could ever remember me.
“離開的時候 我只帶走了身上穿的衣服”
"I left with just the clothes on my back."
我不想再念了 您能不能直接告訴我，他去哪了？
I don't want to read this now. Can you just tell me where he went?
我也不知道
I don't really know.
這是寄給我的，1970年，我才兩歲 “生日快樂”
It's for me. 1970. I was two. "Happy Birthday."
“我希望，可以在你臨睡前，吻你”
"I wish I could have kissed you good night."
都是寄給我的
They're all for me.
五歲，“我希望 可以領著你，上第一天學”
Five. "I wish I could have taken you to your first day of school."
六歲，“我希望 可以在你身邊，教你鋼琴”
Six. "I wish I could have been there to teach you to play piano."
1981年，13歲
1981, 13.
“我希望，可以告訴你 別去追那幫楞頭小子”
"I wish I could have told you not to chase some boy.
“我希望，你傷心的時候，有我安慰”
"I wish I could have held you when you had a broken heart.
“我希望，我可以當你爸爸 再沒有什麼，比這更讓我夢繞”
"I wish I could have been your father. Nothing I ever did will replace that."
我猜他去過印度
I guess he went to India.
“只要是有意義的事 再晚去做還有意義的”
"For what it's worth, it's never too late,
- “不過如果是我說，該說再‘早’…” - 再‘早’去做都是有意義的
- "or, in my case, too early..." - ... or, in my case, too early,
做你想做的人
to be whoever you want to be.
這件事，沒有時間的限制 只要願意，什麼時候都可以開始
There's no time limit. Start whenever you want.
你能從現在開始改變，也可以一成不變 這件事，沒有規矩可言
You can change or stay the same. There are no rules to this thing.
你能活出最精彩的自己 也可能搞得一團糟
We can make the best or the worst of it.
我希望，你能活出最精彩的自己
And I hope you make the best of it.
我希望，你能見識到令你驚奇的事物
I hope you see things that startle you.
我希望，你能體驗未曾體驗過的情感
I hope you feel things you never felt before.
我希望，你能遇見一些想法不同的人
I hope you meet people with a different point of view.
我希望，你為你自己的人生感到驕傲
I hope you live a life you're proud of.
如果你發現自己還沒有做到 我希望，你有勇氣
And if you find that you're not, I hope you have the strength
- 重頭再來 - “重頭再來”
- to start all over again. - "...start all over again."
他離開我們很久
He had been gone a long time.
下週四見了
I'll see you next Thursday.
- 晚安，黛西老師 - 晚安，小甜心
- Good night, Miss Daisy. - Oh, good night, sweetheart.
抱歉，我們要關門了
I'm sorry, we're closing.
有什麼需要幫忙的嗎
Can I help you?
您是來接孩子嗎？
Are you here to pick somebody up?
你為什麼要回來？
Why did you come back?
媽？
Mom?
可以走了吧？
You ready yet?
媽，怎麼了？
Mom, what's wrong?
只是剛剛聽說一個朋友的噩耗
I was just hearing a very sad story about a mutual friend
我都很久沒見過他了
who I hadn't seen for a very long time.
卡洛琳，這是本傑明
Caroline, this is Benjamin.
其實你小時候就認識他了
You knew him when you were just a baby.
- 嗨 - 嗨
- Hi. - Hi.
嘿
Hey.
- 哦，抱歉，我還以為你完事了 - 這位是我家的世交
- Oh, I'm sorry, I thought you were done. - Oh, this is a friend of my family's.
本傑明·巴頓，這是我丈夫，羅伯特
Benjamin Button, this is my husband, Robert.
- 你好 - 幸會
- How do you do? - A pleasure.
嗯，很高興認識你
Well, it was very nice to meet you.
- 我們就在車上等了，親愛的 - 嗯，好
- We'll be in the car, darling. - All right.
拜
Bye.
我去關門
I'm just locking up.
哇
Wow.
她可真美，像她母親
She's beautiful. Like her mother.
- 她跳舞嗎？ - 跳得不是很好
- Does she dance? - Not very well.
估計是遺傳我的吧
I guess that'd be from my side of things.
她是個好姑娘
She's a dear, sweet girl.
只是有點迷惘 不過說回來，誰12歲的時候不是呢
She seems a little lost. But then, who isn't at 12?
她總是讓我想起…你
A lot of her reminds me of you.
我丈夫是個鰥夫，那個…過去是
My husband, he's a widower, or was... Was a widower.
他是個大好人，愛冒險，很陽光
He's an incredibly kind, just bright, adventurous man.
- 他也是個好父親 - 真好
- He's been a terrific father. - Good.
- 你看起來，又年輕了好多 - 只是外表
- You are so much younger. - Only on the outside.
你說得對
You were right.
我沒法同時養你們兩個人
I couldn't have been raising both of you.
我不夠堅強
I'm not that strong.
那你住哪？
So, where are you staying?
接下來準備幹什麼？
What are you gonna do?
我住在龐恰特雷恩旅店
I'm staying at the Pontchartrain Hotel on the Avenue.
也不知道接著該幹什麼
I don't know what I'm gonna do.
不過…
But...
他們在等我
They're waiting.
我還記得，他就是？
I remember that. That was him?
颶風轉向了
The hurricane has changed directions.
不久就登陸
It's going to make landfall sometime soon.
- 我該做些什麼？ - 正在組織撤離人員
- Am I supposed to do something? - Arrangements are being made
不過走不走還是你自己說了算
to move people, but it's up to you.
不了，我們留著
No. No, we're... We're staying.
要是情況有變，我會及時通知你
I'll let you know if anything changes.
“那晚，我正坐著 奇怪自己為什麼要回來”
"That night, while I was sitting and wondering why I came back at all,
“傳來了敲門聲”
"there was a knock at the door."
進來吧
Come in.
你過得好嗎？
Are you all right?
對不起，我都不知道 自己來這是要幹嘛
I'm sorry, I don't know what I'm doing here.
沒什麼是永恆的
Nothing lasts.
我愛你，從沒變過
I have never stopped loving you.
哦，別，本傑明，我太老了
Oh, but, Benjamin, I'm an old woman now.
有些事，你永遠都不會忘記
Some things you never forget.
很少有人知道
... so few people even know
您過去還蹲過監獄
that you were ever in jail in the first place.
告訴您吧，我也覺得不爽
I'll tell you, I am sick about it, too,
因為，拜託，他們就算不給您頒個
because, please, if they're not gonna give you an award
“年度人物”之類的大獎，至少
like "Man of the Year," at least what they could do
也該把您的名字從犯人檔案裡除掉
is stop having you listed as an ex-convict
我覺得，這真是太不公了
which I think is, again, so unfair.
晚安，本傑明
Good night, Benjamin.
晚安，黛西
Good night, Daisy.
和預想的一樣，我看著她離開
And as I knew I would, I watched her go.
後面他就沒寫了
That's the last thing he wrote.
你父親死後的某一天
Sometime after your father passed,
我接到一個電話
there was a call.
喂
Hello.
是我，請講
Yes, speaking.
抱歉，我不太明白
I'm sorry, I don't understand.
在路邊那房子停下
It's the corner house.
請進
Come on in.
- 我是黛西·富勒 - 我叫大衛·埃爾南德斯
- I'm Daisy Fuller. - I'm David Hernandez,
是兒童福利中心奧爾良分局的
with the Orleans Parish Department of Child Welfare Services.
他住在一棟危樓裡
He was living in a condemned building.
警方發現了這個
The police found this with him.
裡面有這個地址 而且很多次提到你的名字
This address. It's got your name in it a lot.
他不太健康，已經去過醫院了
He's in very poor health. He was taken to the hospital.
他似乎都分不清，自己是誰，在哪 好像是糊塗了
He doesn't seem to know who or where he is. He's very confused.
我告訴埃爾南德斯先生了 本傑明和我們一樣
I was telling Mr. Hernandez that Benjamin is one of us.
要是他需要個住的地方，就呆在這吧
If he needs a place to stay, it's all right, he can stay here.
本傑明？
Benjamin?
你彈得真好聽
You play beautifully.
他好像不太喜歡被人碰
He doesn't seem to like to be touched.
他記性時好時壞，不太能認人
He goes in and out of states of recognition.
醫生說，他們也無能為力
The doctors say, if they didn't know any better,
他已經出現癡呆的症狀了
he has the beginnings of dementia.
你還記得我嗎？
Do you remember me?
我是黛西
I'm Daisy.
我叫本傑明
I'm Benjamin.
很高興認識你，本傑明
It's nice to meet you, Benjamin.
你不介意我坐你旁邊吧？ 我很喜歡聽你彈琴
Would you mind if I sit with you? I would love to hear you play.
我認識你嗎？
Do I know you?
- 我要吃早飯 - 此後，每天
- I want some breakfast. - And every day,
我都要過去看看，他過得怎麼樣
I would stop by to make sure that he was comfortable.
- 不，我沒吃過 - 你剛剛吃完了
- No, I didn't. - You just finished eating.
別以為我不知道你們想耍我！
Don't think I don't know what you're doing!
你們這群該死的騙子！
You're all fucking liars!
他不信自己剛吃了早飯
He doesn't believe he just had his breakfast.
哦，咱來想想
Now, why don't we see
給你找點別的事做吧
if we can't find something else for you to do?
我總覺得，自己好像 有很多事情記不得了
I have a feeling there's a lot of things I can't remember.
比如呢？
Well, like what, sugar?
好像我已經活了很久
It's like there's this whole life I had,
卻不記得過去的生活
and I can't remember what it was.
沒事的
It's okay.
即使忘了，也沒事的
It's okay to forget things.
很多時候，他根本不記得 自己是誰，自己在哪
Many times, he would simply forget who or where he was.
他在那，屋頂上
There he is, he's up there on the roof.
照顧他並不容易
It wasn't easy.
- 本傑明！ - 我看見了！
- Benjamin! - I can see everything!
- 我能看見大河！ - 沒錯
- I can see the big river! - That's right,
你當然什麼都看得見，小可愛
you can see everything, sweetheart.
我看得見葬著媽媽的墓地
I can see the graveyard where Mama's buried,
- 那裡還埋著很多其他人 - 快下來！
- and all those other people. - I want you to come down!
- 我要是會飛呢？ - 我認識個人就會飛
- What if I could fly? - I knew a man who could fly.
你下來，我就講他的故事給你聽
You come down and I'll tell you all about him.
誰快上去接他
Somebody go up there.
我搬進去住的時候，他相當於五歲
He was five when I moved in.
差不多就是我認識他時候那麼大
Nearly the same age I was when I had met him.
“畫裡畫的是大袋鼠
"This is the picture of Old Man Kangaroo
下午五點，他終於會蹦蹦跳了
"at 5:00 in the afternoon
他的雙腿又粗又壯又漂亮”
"when he had got his beautiful hind legs."
歲月就這樣流逝
The days passed.
我看著他，不會再走路
And I watched as he forgot how to walk
- 不會再說話 - 我叫什麼呀
- and how to talk. - What's my name?
我叫黛西
I'm Daisy.
你會說“黛西”嗎？
Can you say "Daisy"?
2002年，火車站換了新鐘
In 2002, they put up a new clock in that train station.
2003年，春天
And in the spring of 2003,
他看著我
he looked at me
那一刻，我知道他認出我來了
and I knew that he knew who I was.
接著，他閉上了眼睛，好像是睡著了
And then he closed his eyes as if to go to sleep.
- 我真希望我認識他 - 現在你就認識了
- I wish I'd known him. - Now you do.
媽，我去看看怎麼回事
Mom, I think I should go see what's going on.
晚安，本傑明
Good night, Benjamin.
有些人，生來 就註定可以悠閒地坐在河邊
Some people are born to sit by a river.
有些人，會被閃電擊中
Some get struck by lightning.
有些人，會音樂
Some have an ear for music.
有些人，是藝術家
Some are artists.
有些人，是游泳健將
Some swim.
有些人，懂紐扣
Some know buttons.
有些人，懂莎士比亞
Some know Shakespeare.
有些人，是媽媽
Some are mothers.
有些人，是舞者
And some people dance.
TLF中文字幕站
http://tlfsubs.eastgame.net/